<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?db.chunk.max_depth 3?>
<appendix xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="feedback" xml:lang="ko">
    <info><title>피드백</title></info>
    
    <para>이 섹션에서는 그놈의 버그를 보고하거나, 그놈 프로그램이나 문서에 대한 제안이나 의견을 제시하거나, 그 외에 그놈에 도움을 주는 방법이 쓰여 있습니다.</para>

    <section xml:id="feedback-bugs"><info><title>버그 보고하기</title></info>
      <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: This section is material taken from mate-desktop/desktop-docs/mate-feedback/ Look for existing translations there before translating it all over again :) -->
      <para xml:lang="en">
     If you have found a bug in a MATE application, please
   report it! Developers do read all the bug reports and try to fix
   these bugs. Please try to be as specific as possible when
   describing the circumstances under which the bug shows (What
   commands did you enter? Which buttons did you click?). If there were any
   error messages, be sure to include them, too.  
      </para> 
      <para xml:lang="en">
	The easiest way to report bugs is by using <application>Bug Buddy</application>, MATE's built-in bug reporting tool. This will launch automatically in the event that an application crashes. The details MATE developers need are automatically collected, but you can further help by giving information about what you were doing when the crash took place.
      </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">
	You can also submit bugs and browse the list of known bugs by
	connecting to the <link xlink:href="https://github.com/mate-desktop/">MATE bug tracking
	database</link>.  You will need to register before you can submit any bugs this way. 
      </para>
      
      <para xml:lang="en">
	Please note that some of MATE applications are developed outside of MATE, or by
	commercial companies (these products are still free
	software). For example, <application>blueman</application>, a
	bluetooth application, is developed at <link xlink:href="https://github.com/blueman-project/blueman/">GitHub</link>. Bug reports and
	comments about these products should be directed to the
	respective organization or company. If you are using <application>Bug 
	Buddy</application>, it will automatically send bug reports to
	the correct database.
	</para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="feedback-wishlist"><info><title>제안 및 의견</title></info> 
      <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: This section is material taken from mate-desktop/desktop-docs/mate-feedback/ Look for existing translations there before translating it all over again :) -->      
      <para xml:lang="en"> 
	If you have a suggestion or want to request a new feature for
      one of the applications, it can also be done using the bug
      tracking database. Submit your suggestion as a bug report as
      described in <xref linkend="feedback-bugs"/> and at the appropriate
      step select <guilabel>Severity: Enhancement</guilabel>. 
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="feedback-docs"><info><title>문서에 대한 의견</title></info>
      <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: This section is material taken from mate-desktop/desktop-docs/mate-feedback/ Look for existing translations there before translating it all over again :) -->      
      <para xml:lang="en"> If you found an inaccuracy or misprint in one of MATE
	documents, or have any comments or suggestions about
	documentation, please let us know! The easiest way of doing so
	is by submitting a bug report as explained before and
	selecting <guilabel>Component: docs</guilabel> at appropriate
	steps (or <guilabel>general</guilabel> if there is no
	<guilabel>docs</guilabel> component). If your comment is about
	general MATE documentation (such as <citetitle>MATE Users
	Guide</citetitle>) rather than specific application manual,
	select <guilabel>Product: mate-user-docs</guilabel>.
      </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">
	Alternatively, you can just send your comments by email to the
	<link xlink:href="http://ml.mate-desktop.org/listinfo">MATE
	Documentation Project</link> mailing list.
      </para>
    </section>
    <!-- NOTE TO TRANSLATORS: end of old material -->

    <section xml:id="joinmate"><info><title>그놈 프로젝트에 참여하기</title></info>
      <para>그놈을 즐겁게 사용하시고, 그놈 환경에서 작업하면서 편리함을 느끼시기를 바랍니다. 하지만, 개선의 여지는 언제 어디에도 있습니다.</para>
      <para>그놈 커뮤니티는 여러분을 초대합니다. 약간의 여가 시간을 낼 수 있다면 자유 소프트웨어 커뮤니티에 참여해 주십시오. 참여할 수 있는 여러가지 분야가 있습니다. 그놈에는 프로그래머도 필요하지만, 번역자, 문서 작성, 테스트, 아티스트, 작가 등도 필요합니다.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">For more information on joining MATE, please visit <link xlink:href="http://live.gnome.org/JoinMate">http://live.gnome.org/JoinMate</link>.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">For more information on giving feedback on MATE, such as bug reports, suggestions, and corrections to documentation, see <xref linkend="feedback-bugs"/>.</para>
    </section>
  </appendix>
