<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?db.chunk.max_depth 3?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="caja" xml:lang="th">
    <info><title>การทำงานกับแฟ้ม</title>
    <db:othercredit class="translator">
      <db:personname>
        <db:firstname>Akom Chotiphantawanon</db:firstname>
      </db:personname>
      <db:email>knight2000@gmail.com</db:email>
    </db:othercredit>
    <db:copyright>
      
        <db:year>2016</db:year>
      
      <db:holder>Akom Chotiphantawanon</db:holder>
    </db:copyright>
  </info>
  
  <!-- ID tag preserved for 2.8 compatibility -->
  <anchor xml:id="goscaja-1"/>

  <!-- Desktop Overview / File Manager -->
  <anchor xml:id="gosoverview-56"/>

  <!-- MOVE THIS ANCHOR -->
  <!-- Desktop Overview / File Manager / To Open Files -->
  <anchor xml:id="gosoverview-58"/>

  <!-- MOVE THIS ANCHOR -->
  <!-- Desktop Overview / File Manager / To Move Files -->
  <anchor xml:id="gosoverview-57"/>

  <!-- MOVE THESE ANCHORS -->
  <!-- Desktop Overview / Desktop -->
  <anchor xml:id="gosgetstarted-11"/>
  <!-- Desktop Overview / Desktop / To Open Desktop Objects -->
  <anchor xml:id="gosoverview-29"/>
  <!-- Desktop Overview / Desktop / To Add Objects-->
  <anchor xml:id="gosoverview-19"/>
  <!-- Using the Start Here Location -->
  <anchor xml:id="goscaja-445"/>
  <!-- To Choose a View in Which to Display a File or Folder - (image/text view) -->
  <anchor xml:id="goscaja-100"/>
  <!-- To Modify the Behavior of a View -->
  <anchor xml:id="goscaja-111"/>
  <!-- To Resize an Icon in Icon View - (This can only be done on desktop now) -->
  <anchor xml:id="goscaja-103"/>
  <!-- To Execute Other Actions When Displaying a File -->
  <anchor xml:id="goscaja-73"/>

  <highlights>
    <para>บทนี้จะอธิบายวิธีใช้โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม <application>Caja</application></para>
  </highlights>

  <section xml:id="goscaja-21"><info><title>เกริ่นนำ</title></info>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>introduction</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-22"><info><title>หน้าที่ของโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</title></info>
    <para>โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม <application>Caja</application> ให้ช่องทางที่ง่ายและครบวงจรในการจัดการแฟ้มและโปรแกรมของคุณ คุณสามารถใช้โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มนี้ทำสิ่งต่อไปนี้ได้:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
       <listitem><para>สร้างโฟลเดอร์และเอกสาร</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>แสดงข้อมูลแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>ค้นหาและจัดการแฟ้ม</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>เรียกสคริปต์และเรียกโปรแกรม</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>ปรับแต่งรูปลักษณ์ที่ปรากฏของแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์ต่าง ๆ</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>เปิดตำแหน่งที่อยู่พิเศษบนเครื่องของคุณ</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>เขียนข้อมูลลงซีดีหรือดีวีดี</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>ติดตั้งและถอดถอนแบบอักษร</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    <para>โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มช่วยให้คุณสามารถจัดจำแนกแฟ้มต่าง ๆ ของคุณออกเป็นโฟลเดอร์ได้ โฟลเดอร์สามารถเก็บแฟ้ม และอาจเก็บโฟลเดอร์ซ้อนในโฟลเดอร์ได้ด้วย การใช้โฟลเดอร์สามารถช่วยให้คุณหาแฟ้มที่ต้องการพบได้ง่ายยิ่งขึ้น</para>
    <para><application>Caja</application> ยังสามารถจัดการพื้นโต๊ะได้ด้วย พื้นโต๊ะก็คือบริเวณที่อยู่ด้านหลังรายการต่าง ๆ ทั้งหมดที่มองเห็นได้จากหน้าจอของคุณ พื้นโต๊ะเป็นองค์ประกอบหลักสำหรับการใช้เครื่องคอมพิวเตอร์ของคุณ</para>
    <para xml:lang="en">Every user has a Home Folder. The Home Folder contains all user's files. The desktop is another folder. The desktop contains special icons allowing easy access to the users Home Folder, Trash, and also removable media such as floppy disks, CDs and USB flash drives.</para>
    <para xml:lang="en"><application>Caja</application> is always running while you are using MATE. To open a new <application>Caja</application> window, double-click on an appropriate icon on the desktop such as <guimenuitem>Home</guimenuitem> or <guimenuitem>Computer</guimenuitem>, or choose an item from <xref linkend="places-menu"/> on the top panel.</para>
    <para>ใน MATE สิ่งต่าง ๆ หลายสิ่งล้วนเป็นแฟ้ม เช่น เอกสารของโปรแกรมประมวลคำ ตารางคำนวณ รูปถ่าย ภาพยนตร์ และเพลง</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="caja-presentation"><info><title>การแสดงผลของโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</title></info>
    
    <para xml:lang="en"><application>Caja</application> provides two modes in which you can interact with your filesystem: spatial and browser mode. You may decide which method you prefer and set  <application>Caja</application> to always use this by selecting (or deselecting) <guilabel>Always open in browser windows</guilabel> in the <guilabel>Behavior</guilabel> tab of the <xref linkend="caja-preferences"/>.</para>
    <para xml:lang="en">Browser mode is the default in MATE, but your distributor, vendor, or system administrator may have configured <application>Caja</application> to use spatial mode by default.</para>
    <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-naut-always-use-browser"><info><title xml:lang="en">Dconf-Editor showing the value of always-use-browser key for gsettings org.mate.caja.preferences schema</title></info>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_always_use_browser.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Dconf-Editor showing the value of always-use-browser key for gsettings org.mate.caja.preferences schema.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para>ต่อไปนี้จะอธิบายความแตกต่างระหว่างรูปแบบทั้งสอง:</para>
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry><!-- BROWSER -->
          <term>แบบท่องดู: ท่องดูแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์ต่าง ๆ</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>หน้าต่างโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มจะทำงานเป็นเบราว์เซอร์ ซึ่งสามารถแสดงตำแหน่งใด ๆ ก็ได้ การเปิดโฟลเดอร์ก็จะเปลี่ยนเนื้อหาในหน้าต่างปัจจุบันให้แสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ใหม่นั้น</para>
            <para>นอกจากเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ หน้าต่างท่องดูก็ยังมีแถบเครื่องมือซึ่งจะมีปุ่มคำสั่งและตำแหน่งทั่วไป มีแถบตำแหน่งซึ่งแสดงตำแหน่งปัจจุบันในลำดับชั้นโฟลเดอร์ และแถบด้านข้างซึ่งจะมีข้อมูลชนิดต่าง ๆ</para>
             <para>เมื่อใช้รูปแบบท่องดูนี้ คุณมักจะมีจำนวนหน้าต่างที่เปิดพร้อมกันน้อยกว่า ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมเกี่ยวกับการใช้รูปแบบท่องดูได้ที่ <xref linkend="caja-browser-mode"/></para>
          <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-naut-browser-mode"><info><title xml:lang="en"><application>Caja</application> in browser mode</title></info>
            <screenshot>
              <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_browser_mode.png" format="PNG"/>
                </imageobject>
                <textobject>
                  <phrase>Caja in browser mode.</phrase>
                </textobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </screenshot>
          </figure>
          </listitem>        
        </varlistentry><!-- SPATIAL -->
        <varlistentry>
          <term>รูปแบบพื้นที่: เปิดแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์โดยมองเป็นวัตถุ</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>หน้าต่างโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มจะแทนโฟลเดอร์ใดโฟลเดอร์หนึ่งโดยเฉพาะ การเปิดโฟลเดอร์จะเป็นการเปิดหน้าต่างใหม่สำหรับโฟลเดอร์ที่เปิดนั้น และแต่ละครั้งที่คุณเปิดโฟลเดอร์ใดโฟลเดอร์หนึ่ง คุณจะพบหน้าต่างสำหรับโฟลเดอร์นั้นอยู่ที่ตำแหน่งเดิมในขนาดเท่าเดิมเหมือนกับการเปิดครั้งล่าสุดเสมอ (และนี่คือเหตุผลที่เรียกรูปแบบนี้ว่า 'รูปแบบพื้นที่')</para>
            <para>การใช้รูปแบบพื้นที่อาจทำให้มีหน้าต่างโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มเปิดอยู่บนหน้าจอหลายบานกว่า แต่ในทางกลับกัน ผู้ใช้บางคนพบว่าการแทนแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์ต่าง ๆ เสมือนหนึ่งเป็นวัตถุทางกายภาพที่วางอยู่ที่ตำแหน่งตายตัวนั้น ทำให้ทำงานกับแฟ้มได้ง่ายขึ้น ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมเกี่ยวกับรูปแบบพื้นที่ได้ที่ <xref linkend="caja-spatial-mode"/></para>
        
            <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-naut-spatial-mode"><info><title xml:lang="en">Three Folders Opened in Spatial Mode</title></info>
              <screenshot>
                <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                  <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_spatial_mode.png" format="PNG"/>
                  </imageobject>
                  <textobject>
                    <phrase>Three Folders Opened in Spatial Mode.</phrase>
                  </textobject>
                </mediaobject>
              </screenshot>
            </figure>
            <note>
              <para>โปรดสังเกต ว่าเมื่ออยู่ในรูปแบบพื้นที่ <application>Caja</application> จะแสดงการบ่งชี้โฟลเดอร์ที่เปิดอยู่ด้วยไอคอนที่ต่างจากโฟลเดอร์ปกติ</para>
            </note>
          </listitem>             
        </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>   
  </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ====================================================== Spatial mode -->  
  <section xml:id="caja-spatial-mode"><info><title>รูปแบบพื้นที่</title></info>
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-24"/>

    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>navigating</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para xml:lang="en">The following section describes how to browse your system using the <application>Caja</application> file manager when configured in spatial mode. In spatial mode, each <application>Caja</application> window corresponds to a single folder. When you open a folder its window appears at the same place on the screen as the last time you looked at it. This is the default behavior in <application>Caja</application>.</para>
    <para>ดูการเปรียบเทียบระหว่างรูปแบบท่องดูและรูปแบบพื้นที่ได้ที่ <xref linkend="caja-presentation"/></para>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-510"><info><title>หน้าต่างเชิงพื้นที่</title></info>
      <para>หน้าต่างเชิงพื้นที่จะเปิดบานใหม่ทุกครั้งที่คุณเปิดโฟลเดอร์ การเปิดโฟลเดอร์ ทำได้โดยวิธีใดวิธีหนึ่งต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-25"/><!-- removed id: Displaying Folder Contents -->
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>ดับเบิลคลิกที่ไอคอนของโฟลเดอร์บนพื้นโต๊ะ หรือในหน้าต่างที่เปิดอยู่</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>เลือกโฟลเดอร์ที่ต้องการ แล้วกด <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo></para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>เลือกโฟลเดอร์ที่ต้องการ แล้วกด <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>ลูกศรลง</keycap></keycombo></para></listitem>
        <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Choose an item from the <xref linkend="places-menu"/> on the top panel. Your Home Folder and folders you have bookmarked are listed here. For more on bookmarks, see <xref linkend="caja-bookmarks"/>.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>หากต้องการปิดโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันพร้อมกับเปิดโฟลเดอร์ใหม่ ก็ทำได้โดยกด <keycap>Shift</keycap> ขณะดับเบิลคลิก หรือกด <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>ลูกศรลง</keycap></keycombo></para>

      <para><xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-504"/> แสดงหน้าต่างในรูปแบบพื้นที่ซึ่งแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ "คอมพิวเตอร์"</para>
      <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-504"><info><title xml:lang="en">Contents of a folder in a spatial mode.<indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>file
manager</primary><secondary>icon view</secondary><tertiary>illustration</tertiary></indexterm></title></info>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_spatial_view.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>Displaying a folder in spatial mode.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    <para>ในรูปแบบพื้นที่ หน้าต่าง <application>Caja</application> แต่ละบานจะแสดงตำแหน่งเพียงตำแหน่งเดียวเท่านั้น การเลือกตำแหน่งที่สองก็จะเปิดหน้าต่าง <application>Caja</application> บานที่สอง และการที่หน้าต่างของแต่ละตำแหน่งจำพิกัดตำแหน่งบนหน้าจอที่หน้าต่างถูกเปิดครั้งล่าสุดไว้ ก็ทำให้คุณแยกแยะโฟลเดอร์ต่าง ๆ ได้ง่ายเมื่อเปิดหลายโฟลเดอร์พร้อมกัน</para>
    <para>ผู้ใช้บางคนเห็นว่ารูปแบบพื้นที่นี้ใช้สะดวกกว่า โดยเฉพาะเมื่อต้องการย้ายแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ไปยังตำแหน่งอื่น ในขณะที่บางคนเห็นว่าจำนวนหน้าต่างที่เปิดนั้นเยอะจนน่าตกใจ <xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-naut-spatial-many-open"/> แสดงตัวอย่างของการท่องดูในแบบพื้นที่โดยเปิดตำแหน่งไว้หลายตำแหน่ง</para>
        <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-naut-spatial-many-open"><info><title xml:lang="en">Three Folders Opened in Spatial Mode</title></info>
          <screenshot>
            <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_spatial_mode.png" format="PNG"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject>
                <phrase>Three Folders Opened in Spatial Mode.</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </screenshot>
        </figure>
<note>
<para xml:lang="en">Because spatial mode will fill your screen with <application>Caja</application> windows, it is important to be able to reposition them effectively. By holding the <keycap>Alt</keycap> key and clicking anywhere within the bounds of a <application>Caja</application> window you may reposition it simply, instead of requiring that you reposition it by dragging its title bar.</para>
</note>
  </section>

   <section xml:id="caja-spatial-components"><info><title>องค์ประกอบของหน้าต่างเชิงพื้นที่</title></info>
      <para><xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-85"/> อธิบายองค์ประกอบต่าง ๆ ของหน้าต่างแฟ้ม</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-85"><info><title>องค์ประกอบของหน้าต่างเชิงพื้นที่</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="29.39*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="70.61*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Menubar</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>บรรจุเมนูที่คุณจะใช้สั่งงานต่าง ๆ ในโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</para>
		<para>คุณยังสามารถเปิดเมนูผุดขึ้นจากหน้าต่างโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มได้ โดยคลิกขวาในหน้าต่าง รายการที่ปรากฏในเมนูจะขึ้นอยู่กับว่าคุณคลิกที่ไหน ตัวอย่างเช่น ถ้าคุณคลิกขวาที่แฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ คุณก็สามารถเลือกรายการที่เกี่ยวกับแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ได้ แต่ถ้าคุณคลิกขวาที่พื้นหลังของช่องแสดงผล คุณก็สามารถเลือกรายการที่เกี่ยวกับการแสดงรายการต่าง ๆ ในช่องแสดงผลได้</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
		<anchor xml:id="goscaja-components-view"/>
                <para>ช่องแสดงผล</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>แสดงเนื้อหาของสิ่งต่อไปนี้:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>โฟลเดอร์</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>ไซต์ FTP</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>โฟลเดอร์ใช้ร่วมของวินโดวส์</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>เซิร์ฟเวอร์ WebDAV</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>ตำแหน่งต่าง ๆ ที่ตรงกับ URI พิเศษ</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>แถบสถานะ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>แสดงข้อมูลสถานะ</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>เมนูเลือกโฟลเดอร์แม่</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>รายชื่อดึงลงนี้แสดงลำดับชั้นที่โฟลเดอร์นั้น ๆ อยู่ เลือกโฟลเดอร์แม่ที่ต้องการเปิดจากเมนูนี้ได้</para>
                <tip><para>กด <keycap>Shift</keycap> ค้างไว้ขณะเลือกรายการจากเมนู ถ้าต้องการปิดโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันพร้อมกับการเปิดโฟลเดอร์ใหม่ด้วย</para></tip>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-4"><info><title>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์บ้านของคุณในหน้าต่างเชิงพื้นที่</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>Home location</secondary>
        <see>Home location</see>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>Home location</primary>
        <secondary>displaying</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์บ้าน ทำได้โดยวิธีใดวิธีหนึ่งต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>ดับเบิลคลิกที่วัตถุ <guilabel>บ้าน</guilabel> บนพื้นโต๊ะ</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>จากแถบเมนูในหน้าต่างโฟลเดอร์ เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>ที่หลัก ๆ</guimenu><guimenuitem>โฟลเดอร์บ้าน</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para> 
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>จากแถบเมนูในพาเนลขอบบน เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>ที่หลัก ๆ</guimenu><guimenuitem>โฟลเดอร์บ้าน</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>หน้าต่างเชิงพื้นที่จะแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์บ้านของคุณ</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-511"><info><title>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์แม่</title></info>
      <para>โฟลเดอร์แม่ คือโฟลเดอร์ที่บรรจุโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบัน การแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์แม่ของโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบัน ทำได้โดยวิธีใดวิธีหนึ่งต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu><guimenuitem>เปิดโฟลเดอร์แม่</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>กด <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>ลูกศรขึ้น</keycap></keycombo></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>เลือกรายการจากเมนูเลือกโฟลเดอร์แม่ที่มุมล่างซ้ายของหน้าต่าง</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>หากต้องการปิดโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันพร้อมกับการเปิดโฟลเดอร์แม่ ก็ทำได้โดยกด <keycap>Shift</keycap> ค้างไว้ขณะเลือกรายการจากเมนูเลือกโฟลเดอร์แม่ หรือกด <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>ลูกศรขึ้น</keycap></keycombo></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-512"><info><title>การปิดโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <para>การปิดโฟลเดอร์ อาจทำได้ง่าย ๆ ด้วยการคลิกที่ปุ่มปิดหน้าต่าง แต่วิธีนี้อาจไม่ใช่วิธีที่เร็วนักในการปิดหน้าต่างหลายบาน ถ้าคุณต้องการจะดูแค่โฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันเท่านั้น โดยไม่ต้องการดูโฟลเดอร์ต่าง ๆ ที่คุณเปิดก่อนจะมาถึงโฟลเดอร์ดังกล่าว ก็เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu><guimenuitem>ปิดโฟลเดอร์แม่</guimenuitem></menuchoice> แต่ถ้าคุณต้องการปิดโฟลเดอร์ทั้งหมดที่แสดงอยู่บนหน้าจอ ก็เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu><guimenuitem>ปิดทุกโฟลเดอร์</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-501"><info><title>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์ในหน้าต่างแบบท่องดู</title></info>
      <para>ถ้าคุณต้องการให้แสดงโฟลเดอร์หนึ่งในรูปแบบท่องดู โดยในขณะเดียวกันก็ยังคงทำงานในรูปแบบพื้นที่ต่อไป ก็ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>เลือกโฟลเดอร์ในระหว่างที่อยู่ในรูปแบบพื้นที่</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu><guimenuitem>ท่องดูโฟลเดอร์</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-open-location"><info><title>การเปิดตำแหน่งที่ตั้ง</title></info>
      <para>คุณสามารถเปิดโฟลเดอร์หรือตำแหน่งอื่น ๆ ในการทำงานแบบพื้นที่ได้ ด้วยการพิมพ์ชื่อโฟลเดอร์หรือตำแหน่งดังกล่าว</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice>
	<shortcut>
		<keycombo><keysym>L</keysym></keycombo>
	</shortcut>
	<guimenu>File</guimenu>
	<guimenuitem>Open Location</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice>, and type the path or URI of the location you wish to open.
</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ====================================================== Browser mode -->
  <section xml:id="caja-browser-mode"><info><title>รูปแบบท่องดู</title></info>
    <!-- Viewing Files in a File Browser Window -->
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-210"/>   
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-447"/>

    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>windows</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>หัวข้อต่อไปนี้จะอธิบายวิธีการท่องดูระบบของคุณด้วยโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม <application>Caja</application> ที่ใช้รูปแบบท่องดู เมื่อใช้รูปแบบท่องดู การเปิดโฟลเดอร์จะใช้หน้าต่างโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มปัจจุบันปรับแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ใหม่ที่เปิดนั้น</para>
    <para>ดูการเปรียบเทียบระหว่างรูปแบบท่องดูและรูปแบบพื้นที่ได้ที่ <xref linkend="caja-presentation"/></para>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-492"><info><title>หน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้ม</title></info>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can access the file browser in the following ways:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenuitem>System Tools</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>File Browser</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para xml:lang="en">While in spatial mode you may open a folder in browser mode by right clicking on that folder and choosing <guimenuitem>Browse Folder</guimenuitem>. A new file browser window will then open and display the contents of the selected folder.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para xml:lang="en">If <application>Caja</application> is set to always open browser windows, double clicking any folder will open a browser window, see <xref linkend="goscaja-56"/>.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
      <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-naut-home-browser-mode"><info><title>เนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ในหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้ม</title></info>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_browser_mode.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase> A folder in a file browser window.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <note>
        <para>ในชุดจัดแจกบางชุดของเดสก์ท็อป MATE ปุ่ม <guibutton>บ้าน</guibutton> ในแถบเครื่องมือ อาจถูกเปลี่ยนเป็นอย่างอื่น เช่น <guibutton>เอกสาร</guibutton></para>
      </note>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-493"><info><title>องค์ประกอบของหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้ม</title></info>
        <para><xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-83"/> จะอธิบายองค์ประกอบต่าง ๆ ของหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้ม</para>
        <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-83"><info><title>องค์ประกอบต่าง ๆ ของหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้ม</title></info>
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="29.39*"/>
            <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="70.61*"/>
            <thead>
              <row rowsep="1">
                <entry>
                  <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">Menubar</para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>บรรจุเมนูที่คุณจะใช้สั่งงานต่าง ๆ ในโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</para>
		              <para>คุณยังสามารถเปิดเมนูผุดขึ้นจากหน้าต่างโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มได้ โดยคลิกขวาในหน้าต่าง รายการที่ปรากฏในเมนูจะขึ้นอยู่กับว่าคุณคลิกที่ไหน ตัวอย่างเช่น ถ้าคุณคลิกขวาที่แฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ คุณก็สามารถเลือกรายการที่เกี่ยวกับแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ได้ แต่ถ้าคุณคลิกขวาที่พื้นหลังของช่องแสดงผล คุณก็สามารถเลือกรายการที่เกี่ยวกับการแสดงรายการต่าง ๆ ในช่องแสดงผลได้</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">Toolbar</para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>บรรจุปุ่มที่คุณจะใช้สั่งงานต่าง ๆ ในโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</para>
<itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guibutton>ถอยกลับ</guibutton> กลับไปสู่ตำแหน่งที่เข้าดูก่อนหน้านี้ โดยรายชื่อดึงลงที่อยู่ข้าง ๆ ก็จะบรรจุรายชื่อของตำแหน่งต่าง ๆ ที่เข้าดูล่าสุด เพื่อให้คุณสามารถถอยกลับไปได้เร็วขึ้น</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para xml:lang="en"><guimenu>Forward</guimenu> Performs the opposite function to the <guibutton>Back</guibutton> toolbar item. If you have previously navigated back in time, then this button returns you to the present.</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guibutton>ขึ้น</guibutton> ย้ายขึ้นไปสู่โฟลเดอร์แม่ของโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันหนึ่งระดับ</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guibutton>อ่านใหม่</guibutton> ปรับแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันเสียใหม่</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guibutton>บ้าน</guibutton> เปิดโฟลเดอร์บ้านของคุณ</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guibutton>คอมพิวเตอร์</guibutton> เปิดโฟลเดอร์คอมพิวเตอร์ของคุณ</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para><guibutton>ค้นหา</guibutton> เปิดแถบค้นหา</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                  <para>แถบตำแหน่งที่ตั้ง</para>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                  <para>แถบตำแหน่งที่ตั้ง เป็นเรื่องมือที่มีประสิทธิภาพในการท่องดูคอมพิวเตอร์ของคุณ แถบนี้สามารถปรากฏได้ในสามรูปแบบ ขึ้นอยู่กับรายการที่คุณเลือก ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมเกี่ยวกับแถบตำแหน่งที่ตั้งได้ที่ <xref linkend="caja-location-bar"/> ในรูปแบบทั้งสามนั้น แถบตำแหน่งจะมีรายการต่อไปนี้เสมอ</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>ปุ่ม <guilabel>ขยายเข้า/ออก</guilabel>: ช่วยให้คุณปรับขนาดของรายการต่าง ๆ ที่แสดงในช่องแสดงผลได้</para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>รายชื่อดึงลง <guilabel>มองเป็น</guilabel>: ช่วยให้คุณเลือกวิธีแสดงรายการต่าง ๆ ในช่องแสดงผลได้</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
              		<anchor xml:id="goscaja-540"/>
                  <para>ช่องด้านข้าง</para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>ทำหน้าที่ต่อไปนี้</para>
                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>แสดงข้อมูลเกี่ยวกับแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบัน</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>ช่วยคุณท่องดูแฟ้มต่าง ๆ</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>การแสดงช่องด้านข้าง ทำได้โดยเลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ช่องด้านข้าง</guimenuitem></menuchoice> ช่องด้านข้างจะบรรจุรายชื่อดึงลงที่ช่วยให้คุณเลือกได้ ว่าจะแสดงอะไรในช่องด้านข้าง คุณสามารถเลือกตัวเลือกต่าง ๆ ได้ดังนี้:</para>                
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">
            <guilabel>Places</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>แสดงที่หลัก ๆ ที่น่าสนใจ</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">
            <guilabel>Information</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>แสดงไอคอนและข้อมูลรายละเอียดเกี่ยวกับโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบัน โดยอาจจะมีปุ่มปรากฏในช่องด้านข้างด้วย ปุ่มเหล่านี้ช่วยให้คุณสั่งการต่าง ๆ กับโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันเพิ่มเติมจากการกระทำปริยายได้</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">
            <guilabel>Tree</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>แสดงลำดับชั้นของระบบแฟ้มของคุณ คุณสามารถใช้ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> นี้ ท่องดูแฟ้มต่าง ๆ ของคุณได้</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">
            <guilabel>History</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>แสดงประวัติของแฟ้ม, โฟลเดอร์, ไซต์ FTP, และ URI ต่าง ๆ ที่คุณได้เข้าดูเมื่อเร็ว ๆ นี้</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">
            <guilabel>Notes</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>ช่วยให้คุณเพิ่มหมายเหตุสำหรับแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์ต่าง ๆ ได้</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">
            <guilabel>Emblems</guilabel>
          </para>
          <para>มีตราต่าง ๆ ที่คุณสามารถติดให้กับแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ได้</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>การปิดช่องด้านข้าง ทำได้โดยคลิกที่ปุ่ม <guibutton>X</guibutton> ที่มุมบนขวาของช่องด้านข้าง</para>
                </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
		<anchor xml:id="goscaja-53"/>
                <para>ช่องแสดงผล</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>แสดงเนื้อหาของสิ่งต่อไปนี้:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>โฟลเดอร์</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>ไซต์ FTP</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>โฟลเดอร์ใช้ร่วมของวินโดวส์</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>เซิร์ฟเวอร์ WebDAV</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>ตำแหน่งต่าง ๆ ที่ตรงกับ URI พิเศษ</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>แถบสถานะ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>แสดงข้อมูลสถานะ</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-18"><info><title>การแสดงและซ่อนองค์ประกอบของหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้ม</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>window components, showing
and hiding</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การแสดงหรือซ่อนองค์ประกอบใด ๆ ของหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้มที่อธิบายใน <xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-83"/> ทำได้โดยเลือกรายการต่อไปนี้จากเมนู:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>การซ่อนช่องด้านข้าง เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ช่องด้านข้าง</guimenuitem></menuchoice> หากต้องการแสดงช่องด้านข้างอีก ก็เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ช่องด้านข้าง</guimenuitem></menuchoice> อีกครั้ง หรืออีกทางหนึ่ง คุณอาจกด <keycap>F9</keycap> เพื่อสลับการซ่อน/แสดงช่องด้านข้าง</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>การซ่อนแถบเครื่องมือ เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>แถบเครื่องมือหลัก</guimenuitem></menuchoice> หากต้องการแสดงแถบเครื่องมืออีก ก็เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>แถบเครื่องมือหลัก</guimenuitem></menuchoice> อีกครั้ง</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>การซ่อนแถบตำแหน่งที่ตั้ง เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>แถบตำแหน่ง</guimenuitem></menuchoice> หากต้องการแสดงแถบตำแหน่งที่ตั้งอีก ก็เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>แถบตำแหน่ง</guimenuitem></menuchoice> อีกครั้ง</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>การซ่อนแถบสถานะ เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>แถบสถานะ</guimenuitem></menuchoice> หากต้องการแสดงแถบสถานะอีก ก็เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>แถบสถานะ</guimenuitem></menuchoice> อีกครั้ง</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-location-bar"><info><title>การใช้แถบตำแหน่งที่ตั้ง</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>window components, showing
and hiding</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>แถบตำแหน่งของหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้มสามารถแสดงทั้งช่องป้อนตำแหน่ง แถบปุ่ม หรือช่องค้นหา แต่ละแบบจะมีประโยชน์ในสถานการณ์ต่าง ๆ</para>


    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Button bar</guilabel></para>
        <para>โดยปกติแล้ว หน้าต่างจะแสดงแถบปุ่ม ซึ่งเป็นแถวของปุ่มแทนลำดับชั้นในระบบแฟ้มของตำแหน่งปัจจุบัน โดยแต่ละปุ่มจะแทนแต่ละโฟลเดอร์ที่บรรจุ คุณสามารถคลิกที่ปุ่มเหล่านี้เพื่อกระโดดไปมาระหว่างโฟลเดอร์ต่าง ๆ ในลำดับชั้น คุณสามารถกลับมาที่โฟลเดอร์แรกเริ่มได้ ซึ่งจะเป็นปุ่มสุดท้ายในแถว</para>
        <para>นอกจากนี้ คุณยังสามารถลากปุ่มต่าง ๆ ไปวางที่ตำแหน่งอื่นได้ เพื่อคัดลอกโฟลเดอร์</para>
      <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-903"><info><title xml:lang="en">The button bar</title></info>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_button_bar.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The button bar.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      </listitem>    
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Text Location Bar</guilabel></para>
        <para>แถบตำแหน่งจะแสดงตำแหน่งปัจจุบันเป็นพาธในรูปข้อความ เช่น '/home/user/Documents' ช่องป้อนตำแหน่งนี้มีประโยชน์สำหรับกระโดดไปยังโฟลเดอร์ที่รู้ตำแหน่งอยู่แล้วได้อย่างรวดเร็ว</para>
        <para>การไปยังตำแหน่งใหม่ ทำได้โดยป้อนพาธใหม่หรือแก้ไขพาธปัจจุบัน แล้วกด <keycap>Enter</keycap> ช่องป้อนพาธจะช่วยเติมเต็มชื่อให้โดยอัตโนมัติถ้าสิ่งที่คุณป้อนนั้นเป็นส่วนต้นของชื่อที่เป็นไปได้เพียงชื่อเดียว หากต้องการรับการเติมเต็มที่แนะนำ ก็กด <keycap>Tab</keycap></para>
      <para>หากต้องการใช้แถบตำแหน่งเสมอ ก็คลิกที่ปุ่มสลับที่อยู่ด้านซ้ายของแถบตำแหน่ง</para>
      <para>การสลับไปยังแถบตำแหน่งอย่างเร็ว โดยที่ยังคงใช้แถบปุ่มต่อไป กด <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo> หรือเลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>ไป</guimenu><guimenuitem>ตำแหน่ง</guimenuitem></menuchoice> หรือกด <keycap>ขีดทับตัวแรก (/)</keycap> เพื่อพิมพ์ชื่อพาธโดยเริ่มจากไดเรกทอรีราก แถบตำแหน่งจะกลับมาแสดงเป็นแถบปุ่มอีกครั้งหลังจากที่คุณกด <keycap>Enter</keycap> หรือยกเลิกด้วยปุ่ม <keycap>Escape</keycap></para>
      <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-902"><info><title xml:lang="en">The location bar</title></info>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_go_to_location.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The location bar.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Search bar</guilabel></para>
        <para>การกด <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> หรือคลิกปุ่ม <guibutton>ค้นหา</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ จะทำให้แถบค้นหาปรากฏขึ้น ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมเกี่ยวกับการค้นหาได้ที่ <xref linkend="caja-searching"/> แถบค้นหาจะดีสำหรับการหาตำแหน่งแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์เมื่อคุณไม่แน่ใจเกี่ยวกับตำแหน่งที่แน่นอน</para>
      <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-904"><info><title xml:lang="en">The search bar</title></info>
        <screenshot>
          <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_search_bar.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The search bar.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-499"><info><title>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์บ้านของคุณ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>Home folder</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>Home location</secondary>
        <see>Home location</see>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>Home location</primary>
        <secondary>displaying</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์บ้านอย่างเร็ว ทำได้จากหน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้มด้วยวิธีใดวิธีหนึ่งต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>ไป</guimenu><guimenuitem>โฟลเดอร์บ้าน</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>คลิกที่ปุ่ม <guibutton>บ้าน</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>คลิกที่ปุ่ม <guibutton>บ้าน</guibutton> ในหมวด "ที่หลัก ๆ" ในช่องด้านข้าง</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>หน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้มก็จะแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์บ้านของคุณ</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-500"><info><title>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <para>เนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์สามารถแสดงได้ในมุมมองแบบไอคอนหรือรายการ โดยเลือกรายการในเมนู <guilabel>มองเป็น</guilabel> ในแถบตำแหน่ง ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมเกี่ยวกับมุมมองแบบรายการและแบบไอคอนได้ที่ <xref linkend="goscaja-7"/></para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>ดับเบิลคลิกที่โฟลเดอร์ในช่องแสดงผล</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>ใช้ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> ในช่องด้านข้าง ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมได้ที่ <xref linkend="goscaja-27"/></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>คลิกที่ปุ่มตำแหน่งต่าง ๆ ในแถบตำแหน่ง</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>กด <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo> เพื่อแสดงช่องป้อนตำแหน่ง จากนั้นป้อนชื่อพาธของโฟลเดอร์ที่ต้องการแสดง แล้วกด <keycap>Enter</keycap> ช่องป้อนตำแหน่งสามารถเติมเต็มชื่อโดยอัตโนมัติได้ โดยขณะที่คุณป้อนชื่อพาธ โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มจะอ่านระบบแฟ้มของคุณ และเมื่อคุณป้อนอักขระมากพอที่จะบ่งชี้ถึงไดเรกทอรีหนึ่งได้ โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มก็จะเติมชื่อของไดเรกทอรีนั้นให้</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>ใช้ปุ่ม <guibutton>ถอยกลับ</guibutton> และ <guibutton>เดินหน้า</guibutton> ในแถบเครื่องมือเพื่อท่องไปในประวัติการท่องดูของคุณ</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>การเปลี่ยนไปยังโฟลเดอร์ระดับบนขึ้นไปหนึ่งระดับของโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบัน เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>ไป</guimenu><guimenuitem>เปิดโฟลเดอร์แม่</guimenuitem></menuchoice> หรืออีกวิธีหนึ่ง ทำได้โดยคลิกปุ่ม <guibutton>ขึ้น</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-26"><info><title>การแสดงโฟลเดอร์แม่</title></info>
      <para>โฟลเดอร์แม่ของโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบันที่กำลังเปิดอยู่ หมายถึงโฟลเดอร์ที่ปรากฏเหนือขึ้นไปหนึ่งชั้นในลำดับชั้นของโฟลเดอร์ปัจจุบัน การแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์แม่ ทำได้โดยวิธีใดวิธีหนึ่งต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>กดปุ่ม <guibutton>ขึ้น</guibutton> ในแถบเครื่องมือ</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>ไป</guimenu><guimenuitem>เปิดโฟลเดอร์แม่</guimenuitem></menuchoice> จากแถบเมนู</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>กดปุ่ม <keycap>Backspace</keycap></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-27"><info><title>การใช้โครงสร้างต้นไม้จากช่องด้านข้าง</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>Tree, using </secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>Tree, using</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>แผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> เป็นความสามารถที่มีประโยชน์ที่สุดอย่างหนึ่งของช่องด้านข้าง แผนภาพนี้จะแสดงลำดับชั้นของระบบแฟ้มของคุณ และจัดเตรียมวิธีการที่สะดวกสำหรับท่องดูระบบแฟ้มของคุณ การแสดงแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> ในช่องด้านข้าง ทำได้โดยเลือก <guimenuitem>ต้นไม้</guimenuitem> ที่รายชื่อดึงลงที่ด้านบนของช่องด้านข้าง</para>
<para>ในแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> โฟลเดอร์ที่เปิดจะแทนด้วยลูกศรชี้ลง</para>
      
      <para><xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-34"/> จะอธิบายการกระทำต่าง ๆ ที่คุณสามารถสั่งได้โดยใช้แผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> พร้อมวิธีการสั่ง</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-34"><info><title>การสั่งแผนภาพต้นไม้</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>สิ่งที่ต้องการ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>การกระทำ</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>เปิดแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>เลือก <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> ในรายชื่อดึงลงที่ด้านบนของช่องด้านข้าง</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>ปิดแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>เลือกรายการอื่นในรายชื่อดึงลงที่ด้านบนของช่องด้านข้าง</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>ขยายโฟลเดอร์ในแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>คลิกที่ลูกศรข้าง ๆ โฟลเดอร์ในแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>ยุบโฟลเดอร์ในแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>คลิกที่ลูกศรข้าง ๆ โฟลเดอร์ในแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para>แสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์หนึ่งในช่องแสดงผล</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>เลือกโฟลเดอร์ที่ต้องการในแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>เปิดแฟ้ม</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>เลือกแฟ้มที่ต้องการในแผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel></para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>คุณสามารถปรับแต่งให้แผนภาพ <guilabel>ต้นไม้</guilabel> แสดงเฉพาะโฟลเดอร์ ไม่แสดงแฟ้มได้ ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมได้ที่ <xref linkend="goscaja-438"/></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-5"><info><title>การใช้ประวัติการท่องดูของคุณ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>navigating history list</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>หน้าต่างท่องดูแฟ้มจะคอยติดตามประวัติของแฟ้ม, โฟลเดอร์, ไซต์ FTP และตำแหน่ง URI ต่าง ๆ ที่คุณเปิด และคุณสามารถใช้ประวัติดังกล่าวในการกระโดดกลับมายังตำแหน่งเหล่านี้ได้อย่างรวดเร็ว ประวัติการท่องดูของคุณจะเก็บรายการล่าสุดที่คุณเปิดสิบรายการ</para>
      <para>การล้างประวัติการท่องดูของคุณ ทำได้โดยเลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>ไป</guimenu><guimenuitem>ล้างประวัติ</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-77"><info><title>การท่องไปในประวัติการท่องดูของคุณโดยใช้เมนู "ไป"</title></info>
        <para>การแสดงรายการที่เปิดล่าสุด ทำได้โดยเลือกเมนู <guimenu>ไป</guimenu> ประวัติการท่องดูของคุณจะแสดงอยู่ที่ส่วนล่างสุดของเมนู <guimenu>ไป</guimenu> การเปิดรายการในประวัติ ก็เพียงแต่คลิกที่รายการที่ต้องการ</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-78"><info><title>การท่องไปในประวัติการท่องดูของคุณโดยใช้แถบเครื่องมือ</title></info>
        <para>การใช้แถบเครื่องมือในการท่องไปในประวัติการท่องดูของคุณ ทำได้ด้วยวิธีต่าง ๆ ดังนี้:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>เปิดโฟลเดอร์หรือ URI ในประวัติการท่องดู โดยคลิกที่ปุ่ม <guibutton>ถอยกลับ</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>เปิดโฟลเดอร์หรือ URI ในประวัติการท่องดู โดยคลิกที่ปุ่ม <guibutton>เดินหน้า</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>แสดงรายชื่อแหล่งที่เปิดดูล่าสุด โดยคลิกที่ลูกศรชี้ลงที่อยู่ด้านขวาของปุ่ม <guibutton>ถอยกลับ</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ และเปิดรายการที่ต้องการ โดยคลิกที่รายการนั้น</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>แสดงรายชื่อแหล่งที่คุณเปิดดูหลังจากที่ได้เปิดดูรายการปัจจุบันไปแล้วตามประวัติการท่องดู โดยคลิกที่ลูกศรชี้ลงที่อยู่ด้านขวาของปุ่ม <guibutton>เดินหน้า</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ และเปิดรายการที่ต้องการ โดยคลิกที่รายการนั้น</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-80"><info><title>การท่องไปในประวัติการท่องดูของคุณโดยใช้ช่องประวัติในแถบข้าง</title></info>
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>file manager</primary>
          <secondary>History</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>สั่งแสดงรายชื่อ <guilabel>ประวัติ</guilabel> ในช่องด้านข้าง โดยเลือก <guilabel>ประวัติ</guilabel> จากรายชื่อดึงลงที่ด้านบนของช่องด้านข้าง รายชื่อ <guilabel>ประวัติ</guilabel> นี้ จะแสดงรายการต่าง ๆ ที่คุณเปิดดูล่าสุด</para>
        <para>การแสดงรายการในประวัติการท่องดู ทำได้โดยดับเบิลคลิกที่รายการในรายชื่อ <guilabel>ประวัติ</guilabel></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>  
  
  <!-- ======================================================== Opening -->
  <section xml:id="caja-open-file"><info><title>การเปิดแฟ้ม</title></info>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-28"/>

    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>opening files</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>เมื่อคุณเปิดแฟ้ม โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มจะเรียกการกระทำปริยายสำหรับแฟ้มชนิดนั้น</para>
    <para>ตัวอย่างเช่น การเปิดแฟ้มเพลงจะเล่นเพลงนั้นด้วยโปรแกรมสำหรับเล่นเพลง การเปิดแฟ้มข้อความจะเปิดเครื่องมือแก้ไขข้อความ เพื่อให้คุณอ่านและแก้ไขข้อความได้ และการเปิดแฟ้มรูปภาพ ก็จะแสดงรูปภาพนั้น</para>
    <para>โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มจะตรวจสอบเนื้อหาของแฟ้มเพื่อพิจารณาชนิดของแฟ้ม ถ้าเนื้อหาส่วนต้นไม่ได้บ่งบอกชนิดของแฟ้ม โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มก็จะตรวจสอบ <glossterm>นามสกุลแฟ้ม</glossterm> แทน</para>
    <note><para xml:lang="en">If you open an executable text file, that is, one that Caja considers can be run as a program, then you will be asked what you want to do: run it, or display it in a text editor. You can modify this behavior in <xref linkend="caja-preferences"/>.</para></note>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-29"><info><title>การเรียกการกระทำปริยาย</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>executing default actions
for files</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การเรียกการกระทำปริยายสำหรับแฟ้มหนึ่ง ๆ ทำได้โดยดับเบิลคลิกที่แฟ้มนั้น ตัวอย่างเช่น การกระทำปริยายสำหรับแฟ้มข้อความเปล่า ก็คือการแสดงเนื้อหาในเครื่องมือแสดงข้อความ ในกรณีนี้ คุณก็สามารถดับเบิลคลิกที่แฟ้มเพื่อแสดงเนื้อหาแฟ้มในเครื่องมือแสดงข้อความได้</para>
      <para>คุณสามารถปรับแต่งโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มเพื่อให้สามารถคลิกแค่ครั้งเดียวเพื่อเรียกการกระทำปริยายได้ ดูข้อมูลเพิ่มเติมได้ที่ <xref linkend="goscaja-56"/></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-30"><info><title>การเรียกการกระทำที่ไม่ใช่ค่าปริยาย</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>executing non-default
actions for files</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การเรียกการกระทำที่ไม่ใช่การกระทำปริยายสำหรับแฟ้มหนึ่ง ๆ ทำได้โดยเลือกแฟ้มที่ต้องการกระทำนั้น จากนั้น ที่เมนู <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu></menuchoice> คุณจะพบตัวเลือก "เปิดด้วย" ต่าง ๆ หรืออาจจะเป็นเมนูย่อย <menuchoice><guimenuitem>เปิดด้วย</guimenuitem></menuchoice> คุณก็เลือกตัวเลือกที่ต้องการได้จากรายชื่อดังกล่าว</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-add-actions"><info><title>การเพิ่มการกระทำ</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-204"/><!-- Assigning Actions to Files -->

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>adding actions</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การเพิ่มการกระทำสำหรับแฟ้มชนิดหนึ่ง ๆ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>ในช่องแสดงผล เลือกแฟ้มชนิดที่ต้องการจะเพิ่มการกระทำ</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu><guimenuitem>เปิดด้วยโปรแกรมอื่น</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>เลือกโปรแกรมจากกล่องโต้ตอบ <guilabel>เปิดด้วยโปรแกรม</guilabel> หรือจะเรียกดูระบบแฟ้มเพื่อเลือกโปรแกรมที่คุณต้องการใช้เปิดแฟ้มชนิดนี้ก็ได้</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
       <para>การกระทำที่คุณเลือก จะถูกเพิ่มเข้าในรายชื่อของการกระทำสำหรับแฟ้มชนิดนั้น ๆ และถ้ายังไม่เคยมีการกระทำสำหรับแฟ้มชนิดนั้นมาก่อน การกระทำที่เพิ่มนั้นก็จะกลายเป็นการกระทำปริยาย</para>
       <para>นอกจากนี้ คุณยังสามารถเพิ่มการกระทำได้ในหัวข้อแท็บ <guilabel>เปิดด้วย</guilabel> ภายใต้ <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu><guimenuitem>คุณสมบัติ</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
   </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-75"><info><title>การปรับเปลี่ยนการกระทำ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>modifying actions</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การปรับเปลี่ยนการกระทำสำหรับแฟ้มชนิดหนึ่ง ๆ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>ในช่องแสดงผล เลือกแฟ้มชนิดที่ต้องการปรับเปลี่ยนการกระทำ</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>แฟ้ม</guimenu><guimenuitem>คุณสมบัติ</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
        </listitem>
       <listitem>
          <para>เลือกหัวข้อแท็บ <guilabel>เปิดด้วย</guilabel></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>ใช้ปุ่ม <guibutton>เพิ่ม</guibutton> หรือ <guibutton>เอาออก</guibutton> เพื่อปรับเปลี่ยนรายชื่อของการกระทำ เลือกการกระทำปริยายโดยใช้ตัวเลือกที่อยู่ทางซ้ายของรายชื่อ</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>    
   
  <!-- =========================================== Searching -->    
  </section>

  <section xml:id="caja-searching"><info><title>การค้นหาแฟ้ม</title></info>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>searching files</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม <application>Caja</application> มีวิธีที่ง่ายและใช้สะดวกสำหรับค้นหาแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์ของคุณ การเริ่มค้นหา ทำได้โดยกด <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> หรือกดปุ่ม <guibutton>ค้นหา</guibutton> บนแถบเครื่องมือ จะปรากฏแถบค้นหาดังแสดงใน <xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-925"/></para>
                    <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-925"><info><title xml:lang="en">The search bar</title></info>
                      <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_search_bar.png" format="PNG"/>
                          </imageobject>
                          <textobject>
                            <phrase>The search bar.</phrase>
                          </textobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>
<para>ป้อนอักขระที่มีในชื่อหรือเนื้อหาของแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ที่คุณต้องการค้นหา แล้วกด <keycap>Enter</keycap> จะปรากฏผลการค้นหาในช่องแสดงผล ตามตัวอย่างใน  <xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-926"/></para>
                    <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-926"><info><title xml:lang="en">The result of a search</title></info>
                      <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_search_results.png" format="PNG"/>
                          </imageobject>
                          <textobject>
                            <phrase>The result of a search.</phrase>
                          </textobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>
<para xml:lang="en">If you are not happy with your search, you can refine it by adding addition conditions. This allows you to restrict the search to a specific file type or location. To add search conditions click the <guibutton>+</guibutton> icon. <xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-927"/> shows a search which has been restricted to the users home directory and to only search for text files.</para>
                    <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-927"><info><title xml:lang="en">Restricting a search</title></info>
                      <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_refine_search.png" format="PNG"/>
                          </imageobject>
                          <textobject>
                            <phrase>Restricting a search.</phrase>
                          </textobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>

    <section xml:id="caja-saving-searches"><info><title>การบันทึกการค้นหา</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>executing default actions for files</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การค้นหาของ Caja ยังสามารถเก็บบันทึกไว้เพื่อใช้ในอนาคตได้ เมื่อบันทึกไว้แล้ว ก็สามารถเปิดผลการค้นหาขึ้นมาใหม่ได้ในภายหลัง <xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-935"/> แสดงรายการค้นหาที่ผู้ใช้บันทึกไว้สามรายการ โดยเปิดดูหนึ่งในสามรายการนั้น</para>
                    <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-935"><info><title xml:lang="en">Browsing the results of a saved search</title></info>
                    
                      <screenshot>
                        <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                          <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_restore_saved_search.png" format="PNG"/>
                          </imageobject>
                          <textobject>
                            <phrase>Browsing the results of a saved search.</phrase>
                          </textobject>
                        </mediaobject>
                      </screenshot>
                    </figure>
<para>ผลการค้นหาที่บันทึกไว้ จะประพฤติเหมือนโฟลเดอร์ปกติทุกประการ ตัวอย่างเช่น คุณสามารถเปิด ย้าย หรือลบแฟ้มจากในผลการค้นหาที่บันทึกไว้ได้</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- =========================================== Managing -->
  <section xml:id="goscaja-8"><info><title>การจัดการแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>managing files and folders</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>หัวข้อนี้อธิบายวิธีทำงานกับแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์</para>

  	<section xml:id="caja-directories-file-systems" status="complete"><info><title>ไดเรกทอรีและระบบแฟ้ม</title></info>
				<para xml:lang="en">In Linux and other Unix-like operating systems, the filesystem is organised in a hierarchical, tree-like structure.  The highest level of the filesystem is the <filename>/</filename> or <emphasis>root directory</emphasis>.  These operating systems create a virtual file system, in which a filesystem object, such as a file or a directory, is represented by an inode. Each inode stores information about its parent and children, as well as its own attributes, among others, the owner, the permissions, the last change, access or modification of the filesystem object.
  				</para>
  				<para>ตัวอย่างเช่น <filename>/home/jebediah/cheeses.odt</filename> เป็นตัวอย่างชื่อพาธเต็มของแฟ้ม <filename>cheeses.odt</filename> ซึ่งอยู่ในไดเรกทอรี <filename>jebediah</filename> ที่อยู่ใต้ไดเรกทอรี <filename>home</filename> ซึ่งอยู่ใต้ไดเรกทอรีราก (<filename>/</filename>) อีกทอดหนึ่ง</para>
				<para xml:lang="en">Underneath the root (<filename>/</filename>) directory, there is a set of important directories, or symbolic links to directories:
  				</para>
  					<itemizedlist>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/bin</filename> - โปรแกรมไบนารี (<emphasis>bin</emphasis>ary) ที่สำคัญ</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/boot</filename> - แฟ้มที่จำเป็นสำหรับการบูต (<emphasis>boot</emphasis>) เครื่องคอมพิวเตอร์</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/dev</filename> - แฟ้มอุปกรณ์ (<emphasis>dev</emphasis>ice) ต่าง ๆ</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/etc</filename> - แฟ้มค่าตั้ง, สคริปต์สำหรับเริ่มงานต่าง ๆ ฯลฯ (<emphasis>etc</emphasis>...)</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/home</filename> - ไดเรกทอรีบ้าน (<emphasis>home</emphasis>) ของผู้ใช้ต่าง ๆ ในระบบ</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/lib</filename> - ไลบรารี (<emphasis>lib</emphasis>rary) ของระบบ</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/lost+found</filename> - ตระเตรียมระบบกู้คืน (<emphasis>lost+found</emphasis>) สำหรับแฟ้มที่อยู่ใต้ไดเรกทอรีราก (<filename>/</filename>)</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/media</filename> - สื่อ (<emphasis>media</emphasis>) ถอดเสียบที่มีการเมานท์ (หรือโหลด) เช่น แผ่นซีดี กล้องดิจิทัล ฯลฯ</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/mnt</filename> - ระบบแฟ้มสำหรับการเมานท์ (<emphasis>m</emphasis>ou<emphasis>nt</emphasis>)</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/opt</filename> - เป็นตำแหน่งสำหรับติดตั้งโปรแกรมที่เป็นตัวเลือกเสริม (<emphasis>opt</emphasis>ional)</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/proc</filename> - ไดเรกทอรีพิเศษแบบพลวัติที่คอยดูแลข้อมูลเกี่ยวกับสถานะของระบบ รวมถึงโพรเซส (<emphasis>proc</emphasis>ess) ต่าง ๆ ที่กำลังทำงานอยู่</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/root</filename> - ไดเรกทอรีบ้านของผู้ใช้ <emphasis>root</emphasis> อ่านว่า 'slash-root'</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/sbin</filename> - โปรแกรมไบนารีของระบบ (<emphasis>s</emphasis>ystem <emphasis>bin</emphasis>ary) ที่สำคัญ</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/srv</filename> - เป็นตำแหน่งสำหรับข้อมูลต่าง ๆ ที่ใช้โดยโปรแกรมให้บริการ หรือเซิร์ฟเวอร์ (<emphasis>s</emphasis>e<emphasis>rv</emphasis>er)</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/sys</filename> - เก็บข้อมูลเกี่ยวกับระบบ (<emphasis>sys</emphasis>tem)</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/tmp</filename> - แฟ้มชั่วคราว (<emphasis>t</emphasis>e<emphasis>mp</emphasis>orary) ต่าง ๆ</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/usr</filename> - โปรแกรมและแฟ้มต่าง ๆ ที่มีไว้ให้ผู้ใช้ (<emphasis>us</emphasis>e<emphasis>r</emphasis>) เข้าใช้</para>
  						</listitem>
  						<listitem>
  							<para><filename>/var</filename> - แฟ้มที่มีการเปลี่ยนแปลง (<emphasis>var</emphasis>iable) อยู่เสมอ เช่นปูมและฐานข้อมูล</para>
  						</listitem> 
  					</itemizedlist>
				<note><para xml:lang="en">More detailed information on the UNIX-like filesystem hierarchy is available at Filesystem Hierarchy Standard 3.0 <link xlink:href="http://refspecs.linuxfoundation.org/fhs.shtml">http://refspecs.linuxfoundation.org/fhs.shtml</link>.</para></note>
  	</section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-7"><info><title>การใช้มุมมองแบบต่าง ๆ ในการแสดงแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>viewer components</primary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>views</secondary>
        <tertiary>introduction</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม ประกอบด้วยมุมมองแบบต่าง ๆ ซึ่งสามารถแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ในลักษณะต่าง ๆ ได้ คือ มุมมองแบบไอคอน และมุมมองแบบรายชื่อ</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>มุมมองแบบไอคอน</para>
          <para xml:lang="en"><xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-naut-icon-view"/> Shows the items in the folder as icons.
          <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-naut-icon-view"><info><title xml:lang="en">The Home Folder displayed in an icon view</title></info>
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_spatial_icon_view.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Your Home Folder displayed in an icon view.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
          </figure></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>มุมมองแบบรายชื่อ</para>
          <para xml:lang="en"><xref linkend="goscaja-FIG-naut-list-view"/> Shows the items in the folder as a list.
          <figure xml:id="goscaja-FIG-naut-list-view"><info><title xml:lang="en">The Home Folder displayed in a list view</title></info>
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_spatial_list_view.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Your Home Folder displayed in a list view.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
          </figure>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>คุณสามารถใช้เมนู <guilabel>มุมมอง</guilabel> หรือรายชื่อแบบดึงลง <guilabel>มองเป็น</guilabel> ในการเลือกมุมมองระหว่างแบบไอคอนกับแบบรายชื่อได้ คุณสามารถระบุวิธีการจัดเรียง หรือเรียงลำดับรายการของโฟลเดอร์ และปรับขนาดของรายการที่แสดงในช่องแสดงผลได้ หัวข้อต่อไปนี้จะอธิบายวิธีการทำงานกับมุมมองแบบไอคอนและมุมมองแบบรายชื่อ</para>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-101"><info><title>การจัดเรียงแฟ้มในมุมมองแบบไอคอน</title></info>
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>file manager</primary>
          <secondary>icon view</secondary>
          <tertiary>arranging files in</tertiary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>เมื่อแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ในแบบไอคอน คุณสามารถระบุวิธีการจัดเรียงรายการต่าง ๆ ของโฟลเดอร์ได้ โดยเลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guisubmenu>จัดเรียงรายการ</guisubmenu></menuchoice> เมนูย่อย <guisubmenu>จัดเรียงรายการ</guisubmenu> จะมีหัวข้อต่าง ๆ ต่อไปนี้:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>รายการแรก จะเป็นตัวเลือกที่ให้คุณจัดเรียงแฟ้มเอง</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>หัวข้อตรงกลาง จะเป็นตัวเลือกต่าง ๆ ที่ให้คุณเรียงลำดับแฟ้มแบบอัตโนมัติได้</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>หัวข้อด้านล่าง จะเป็นตัวเลือกต่าง ๆ ที่ช่วยให้คุณปรับพฤติกรรมการจัดเรียงแฟ้มได้</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>เลือกตัวเลือกที่เหมาะสมจากเมนูย่อยดังกล่าว ดังอธิบายในตารางต่อไปนี้:</para>
        <informaltable frame="topbot">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colname="colspec6" colwidth="28.75*"/>
            <colspec colname="colspec7" colwidth="71.25*"/>
            <thead>
              <row rowsep="1">
                <entry>
                  <para xml:lang="en">Option</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Manually</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>เลือกตัวเลือกนี้ถ้าต้องการจัดเรียงรายการต่าง ๆ เอง การจัดเรียง ทำได้โดยลากรายการต่าง ๆ ไปยังตำแหน่งที่ต้องการภายในช่องแสดงผล</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="colspec6" valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>By Name</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="colspec7" valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to sort the
items alphabetically by name. The order of the items is not case-sensitive.
If the file manager is set to display hidden files, the hidden files are shown
last.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="colspec6" valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>By Size</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="colspec7" valign="top">
                  <para>เลือกตัวเลือกนี้ถ้าต้องการเรียงลำดับรายการตามขนาด จากใหญ่ไปเล็ก เมื่อคุณเรียงลำดับตามขนาด โฟลเดอร์จะถูกเรียงตามจำนวนรายการในโฟลเดอร์ ไม่ใช่ตามขนาดรวมของรายการต่าง ๆ ในโฟลเดอร์</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="colspec6" valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>By Type</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="colspec7" valign="top">
                  <para>เลือกตัวเลือกนี้ถ้าต้องการเรียงรายการตามลำดับอักษรของชนิดของรายการ โดยจะเรียงตามลำดับอักษรของ <firstterm>ชนิด MIME</firstterm> ซึ่งชนิด MIME นี้ จะบ่งชี้รูปแบบของข้อมูลแฟ้ม และช่วยให้โปรแกรสามารถหาวิธีอ่านแฟ้มได้ ตัวอย่างเช่น โปรแกรมอีเมลจะสามารถทราบได้ว่ามีแฟ้มชนิด PNG แนบมากับเมลได้จากชนิด MIME <literal>image/png</literal> นี่เอง</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="colspec6" valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>By Modification Date</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="colspec7" valign="top">
                  <para>เลือกตัวเลือกนี้ถ้าต้องการเรียงรายการตามวันเวลาที่รายการมีการเปลี่ยนแปลงล่าสุด โดยแฟ้มที่มีการเปลี่ยนแปลงล่าสุดจะมาก่อน</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="colspec6" valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>By Emblems</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="colspec7" valign="top">
                  <para>เลือกตัวเลือกนี้ถ้าต้องการเรียงรายการตามตราที่ได้ติดไว้ โดยเรียงตามลำดับอักษรของชื่อตรา รายการที่ไม่มีตราจะมาท้ายสุด</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry colname="colspec6" valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Compact Layout</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry colname="colspec7" valign="top">
                  <para>เลือกตัวเลือกนี้ถ้าต้องการจัดเรียงรายการให้กระชับเข้าหากันมากขึ้น</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Reversed Order</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para>เลือกตัวเลือกนี้ถ้าต้องการย้อนลำดับการเรียงของวิธีเรียงที่เลือกไว้ ตัวอย่างเช่น ถ้าคุณเลือกให้เรียงรายการตามชื่อ ตัวเลือก <guilabel>เรียงแบบย้อนกลับ</guilabel> ก็จะเรียงรายการตามลำดับอักษรจากหลังมาหน้า</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-listview-arrange"><info><title>การจัดเรียงแฟ้มในมุมมองแบบรายชื่อ</title></info>
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>file manager</primary>
          <secondary>list view</secondary>
          <tertiary>arranging files in</tertiary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>เมื่อแสดงเนื้อหาของโฟลเดอร์ในแบบรายชื่อ คุณสามารถระบุวิธีการจัดเรียงรายการต่าง ๆ ของโฟลเดอร์ได้ โดยคลิกที่ส่วนหัวของคอลัมน์ที่ระบุคุณสมบัติที่คุณต้องการให้ใช้เรียงลำดับรายการ หากต้องการเรียงลำดับย้อนกลับ ก็คลิกที่หัวคอลัมน์เดิมซ้ำอีกครั้ง</para>
        <para>การเพิ่มหรือลดคอลัมน์ที่จะแสดงในมุมมองแบบรายชื่อ ทำได้โดยเลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guisubmenu>คอลัมน์ที่แสดง</guisubmenu></menuchoice></para>
        <para>โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มจะจดจำวิธีการจัดเรียงรายการของแต่ละโฟลเดอร์ไว้ และเมื่อคุณเปิดโฟลเดอร์เดิมครั้งต่อไป รายการต่าง ๆ ก็จะจัดเรียงเหมือนที่คุณเลือกไว้นี้ หรืออีกนัยหนึ่ง เมื่อคุณกำหนดวิธีจัดเรียงรายการในโฟลเดอร์ ก็เป็นการปรับแต่งโฟลเดอร์ให้แสดงรายการในแบบที่คุณกำหนดนั่นเอง หากต้องการย้อนโฟลเดอร์คืนสู่วิธีจัดเรียงแบบปริยายที่กำหนดไว้ในค่าปรับแต่งของคุณ ก็ทำได้โดยเลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ใช้มุมมองปริยาย</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
      </section>

<section xml:id="goscaja-102"><info><title>การเปลี่ยนขนาดของรายการต่าง ๆ ในมุมมอง</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>zooming in and out</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>คุณสามารถเปลี่ยนขนาดของรายการต่าง ๆ ที่แสดงได้ ด้วยวิธีการต่าง ๆ ดังนี้:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>การเพิ่มขนาดของรายการที่แสดง เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ขยายเข้า</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>การลดขนาดของรายการที่แสดง เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ขยายออก</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>การย้อนคืนมาแสดงรายการที่ขนาดปกติ เลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ขนาดปกติ</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>นอกจากนี้ คุณยังสามารถใช้ปุ่มขยายเข้า-ขยายออกในแถบตำแหน่งของหน้าต่างท่องดู เพื่อปรับขนาดของรายการที่แสดงได้ <xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-42"/> จะอธิบายวิธีการใช้ปุ่มขยายเข้า-ขยายออก</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-42"><info><title>ปุ่มขยายเข้า-ขยายออก</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="21.98*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="32.86*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="44.17*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>ปุ่ม</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>ชื่อปุ่ม</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_zoom_out_button.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Zoom Out button.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>ปุ่ม <guibutton>ขยายออก</guibutton></para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para>คลิกที่ปุ่มนี้ถ้าต้องการลดขนาดของรายการที่แสดง</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_normal_size_button.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Normal Size button.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>ปุ่ม <guibutton>ขนาดปกติ</guibutton></para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>คลิกที่ปุ่มนี้ถ้าต้องการย้อนคืนมาแสดงรายการที่ขนาดปกติ</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_zoom_in_button.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Zoom In button.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para>ปุ่ม <guibutton>ขยายเข้า</guibutton></para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para>คลิกที่ปุ่มนี้ถ้าต้องการขยายขนาดของรายการที่แสดง</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>โปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้มจะจดจำขนาดของรายการที่แสดงในแต่ละโฟลเดอร์ไว้ และเมื่อคุณเปิดโฟลเดอร์เดิมครั้งต่อไป รายการต่าง ๆ ก็จะแสดงที่ขนาดที่คุณเลือกไว้นี้ หรืออีกนัยหนึ่ง เมื่อคุณปรับขนาดการแสดงรายการในโฟลเดอร์ ก็เป็นการปรับแต่งโฟลเดอร์ให้แสดงรายการที่ขนาดที่คุณกำหนดนั่นเอง หากต้องการย้อนโฟลเดอร์คืนสู่การแสดงที่ขนาดปริยายที่กำหนดไว้ในค่าปรับแต่งของคุณ ก็ทำได้โดยเลือก <menuchoice><guimenu>มุมมอง</guimenu><guimenuitem>ใช้มุมมองปริยาย</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
    </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-select"><info><title>การเลือกแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-202"/>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>selecting files and folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can select files and folders in several
ways in the file manager. Typically, this is achieved by clicking on the files using the mouse, as explained in <xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-10"/>. In addition, <xref linkend="caja-select-pattern"/> describes how to select a group of files matching a specific pattern.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-10"><info><title xml:lang="en">Selecting Items in the File Manager</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="36.36*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="63.64*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>สิ่งที่ต้องการ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2">
                <para>การกระทำ</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select an item</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Click on the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select a group of contiguous items</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">In icon view, drag around the files that you want to select.</para>
                <para xml:lang="en">In list view, click
on the first item in the group. Press-and-hold <keycap>Shift</keycap>, then
click on the last item in the group.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select multiple items</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Press-and-hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>.
Click on the items that you want to select.</para>
                <para xml:lang="en">Alternatively, press-and-hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, then drag around the files that you want to select.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select all items in a folder</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Select All Files</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para xml:lang="en">To perform the default action on an item, double-click on the item.
You can set your file manager preferences so that you click once on a file
to execute the default action. For more information, see <xref linkend="goscaja-56"/>.</para>

<section xml:id="caja-select-pattern"><info><title>การเลือกแฟ้มที่ตรงกับแพตเทิร์นเฉพาะ</title></info>
<para xml:lang="en"><application>Caja</application> allows you to select all files matching a pattern based upon their filename and an optional number of wildcards. This can be useful if, for example, you wish to select all files which contain the phrase "memo" in their filename. <xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-select-pattern"/> gives some examples of possible patterns and the resulting files they would match.</para>
<table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-select-pattern"><info><title xml:lang="en">Selecting Items in the File Manager</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="36.36*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="63.64*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>รูปแบบ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2">
                <para xml:lang="en">Files Matched</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">note.*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">This pattern would match files called note, with any extension.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">*.ogg</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">This pattern would match all files with the .ogg extension</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">*memo*</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">This pattern would match all files or folders whose name contains the word memo.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para xml:lang="en">To perform the Select Pattern command Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Select Patterns</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the menu. After entering the desired pattern you are left with those files or folders which matched the pattern selected. You may then do with the selected files or folders what you choose.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-dragndrop"><info><title>การลากวางในโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-201"/>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>drag-and-drop</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can use drag-and-drop to perform several tasks in the
file manager. When you drag-and-drop, the mouse pointer provides feedback
about the task that you perform. <xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-11"/> describes
the tasks that you can perform with drag-and-drop. The table also shows the
mouse pointers that appear when you drag-and-drop.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-11"><info><title>การลากวางในโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="36.36*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="98.56*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="28.70*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>สิ่งที่ต้องการ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2">
                <para>การกระทำ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Mouse Pointer</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Move an item</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Drag the item to the new location.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/move_pointer.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Move pointer.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Copy an item</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Grab the item, then press-and-hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>. Drag the item to the location where you want the copy to reside.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/copy_pointer.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Copy pointer.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Create a symbolic link to an item</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Grab the
item, then press-and-hold <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>.
Drag the item to the location where you want the symbolic link to reside.</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/link_pointer.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Symbolic link pointer.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Ask what to do with the item you drag</para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Grab the item, then press-and-hold <keycap>Alt</keycap>. You may also use the middle mouse button to perform the same operation.
Drag the item to the location where you want the item to reside. Release the mouse button.
A popup menu appears. Choose one of the following items from the popup menu:</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para xml:lang="en">
                      <guimenuitem>Move here</guimenuitem>
                    </para>
                    <para xml:lang="en">Moves the item to the location.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para xml:lang="en">
                      <guimenuitem>Copy here</guimenuitem>
                    </para>
                    <para xml:lang="en">Copies the item to the  location.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para xml:lang="en">
                      <guimenuitem>Link here</guimenuitem>
                    </para>
                    <para xml:lang="en">Creates a symbolic link to the item at the location.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para xml:lang="en">
                      <guimenuitem>Set as Background</guimenuitem>
                    </para>
                    <para xml:lang="en">If the item is an image, sets the image to be the background.
 You can use this command to set the background of the desktop, the side pane or the view pane.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  <listitem>
                    <para xml:lang="en">
                      <guimenuitem>Cancel</guimenuitem>
                    </para>
                    <para xml:lang="en">Cancels the drag-and-drop operation.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/ask_pointer.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Ask pointer.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-9"><info><title>การย้ายแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>moving files and folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can move a file or folder by dragging it with the mouse, or with the cut and paste commands. The following sections describe these two methods.</para>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-537"><info><title>ลากไปวางที่ตำแหน่งที่ตั้งใหม่</title></info>
        <para xml:lang="en">To drag a file or folder to a new location, perform the following steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Open two file manager windows:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
	            <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The window containing the item you want to move.</para></listitem>
	            <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The window you want to move it to, or the window containing the folder you want to move it to.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Drag the file or folder that you want to move to the new location. If the new location is a window, drop it anywhere in the window. If the new location is a folder icon, drop the item you are dragging on the folder.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para xml:lang="en">To move the file or folder to a folder that is one level below the current
location, do not open a new window. Instead, drag the file or folder to the
new location in the same window.</para>
        <tip><para xml:lang="en">For more on dragging items, see <xref linkend="caja-dragndrop"/>.</para></tip>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-538"><info><title>ตัดไปแปะที่ตำแหน่งที่ตั้งใหม่</title></info>
        <para xml:lang="en">You can cut a file or folder and paste the file or folder into another
folder, as follows:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder that you want to move, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Cut</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Open the folder to which you want to move the file or folder,
then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Paste
</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-10"><info><title>การคัดลอกแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>copying files and folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can copy a file or folder by dragging it with the mouse, or with the copy and paste commands. The following sections describe these two methods.</para>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-640"><info><title>ลากไปวางที่ตำแหน่งที่ตั้งใหม่</title></info>
        <para>การคัดลอกแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Open two file manager windows:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
	            <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The window containing the item you want to move.</para></listitem>
	            <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The window you want to move it to, or the window containing the folder you want to move it to.</para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Drag the file or folder that you want to move to the new location. Press-and-hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> either before or during the drag. If the new location is a window, drop it anywhere in the window. If the new location is a folder icon, drop the item you are dragging on the folder.</para>
          </listitem>          
        </orderedlist>
        <para xml:lang="en">To copy the file or folder to a folder that is one level below the current
location, do not open a new window. Instead, grab the file or folder, then
press-and-hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>. Drag the file or folder to the new location
in the same window.</para>
        <tip><para xml:lang="en">For more on dragging items, see <xref linkend="caja-dragndrop"/>.</para></tip>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-441"><info><title>คัดลอกไปแปะที่ตำแหน่งที่ตั้งใหม่</title></info>
        
        <para xml:lang="en">You can copy a file or folder and paste the file or folder into another
folder, as follows:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder that you want to copy, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Open the folder to which you want to copy the file or folder,
then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Paste
</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-82"><info><title>การทำสำเนาแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>duplicating files and
folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">To create a copy of a file or folder
in the current folder, perform the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder that you want to duplicate.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Duplicate</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          <para xml:lang="en">A copy of the file or folder appears in the current folder.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-11"><info><title>การสร้างโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>creating folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การสร้างโฟลเดอร์ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Open the folder where you want to create the new folder.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, right-click
on the background of the window, then choose <guimenuitem>Create Folder</guimenuitem>.</para>
          <para xml:lang="en">An <guilabel>untitled</guilabel> folder is added to the location. The
name of the folder is selected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Type a name for the folder, then press <keycap>Return</keycap>. </para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-templates-docs"><info><title>แม่แบบและเอกสาร</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>creating documents</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can create templates from documents that you frequently
create. For example, if you often create invoices, you can create an empty
invoice document and save the document as <literal>invoice.doc</literal> in
the <literal>$HOME/Templates</literal> folder.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can also access the templates folder from a file browser window.
Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Go</guimenu><guimenuitem>Templates</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">The template name is displayed as a submenu item in the <guilabel>Create
Document</guilabel> menu.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can also create subfolders in the template folder. Subfolders display
as submenus in the menu. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can also share templates. Create a symbolic link from the template
folder to the folder containing the shared templates. </para>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-514"><info><title>การสร้างเอกสาร</title></info>
        <para xml:lang="en">If you have document templates, you can choose to create a document
from one of the installed templates. </para>
        <para>การสร้างเอกสาร ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Select the folder where you want to create the new document.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Create Document</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, right-click on
the background of the view pane, then choose <guimenuitem>Create Document</guimenuitem>.</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">The names of any available templates are displayed as submenu items
from the <guilabel>Create Document</guilabel> menu.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Double-click on the template name for the document that you
want to create. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Rename the document before saving to the appropriate folder.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-12"><info><title>การเปลี่ยนชื่อแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>renaming folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การเปลี่ยนชื่อแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder that you want to rename.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, right-click on the file
or folder, then choose <guimenuitem>Rename</guimenuitem>.</para>
          <para xml:lang="en">The name of the file or folder is selected.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Type a new name for the file or folder, then press <keycap>Return</keycap>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-13"><info><title>การย้ายแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ไปทิ้งลงถังขยะ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>Trash</secondary>
        <see>Trash</see>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>Trash</primary>
        <secondary>moving files or folders to</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">To move a file or folder
to <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> perform the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder that you want to move to <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Move to Trash</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, right-click on the
file or folder, then choose <guimenuitem>Move to Trash</guimenuitem>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para xml:lang="en">Alternatively, you can drag the file or folder to the <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> object on the desktop.</para>
      <note>
        <para xml:lang="en">When you move a file or folder from a removable media to <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>, the file or folder is stored in a <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>
location on the removable media. To remove the file or folder permanently
from the removable media, you must empty <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-443"><info><title>การลบแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>deleting files or folders</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">When you delete a file or folder, the file or
folder is not moved to <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>, but is deleted from your
file system immediately. The <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> menu item is
only available if you select the <guilabel>Include a Delete command that bypasses
Trash</guilabel> option in the <guilabel>File Management Preferences</guilabel>
 dialog. </para>
      <para>การลบแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder that you want to delete.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Alternatively, right-click on the file
or folder, then choose <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para xml:lang="en">
	Alternatively, select the file or folder you want to delete, and press <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Del</keycap></keycombo>. 
	<note>
	  <para xml:lang="en">
	    This shortcut is independent from the <guilabel>Include a Delete command that bypasses Trash</guilabel> option. 
	  </para>
	</note>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="caja-symlink"><info><title>การสร้างจุดเชื่อมโยงไปยังแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-14"/>        
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>creating symbolic link</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>symbolic link</primary>
        <secondary>to file or folder, creating</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">A symbolic link is
a special type of file that points to another file or folder. When you perform
an action on a symbolic link, the action is performed on the file or folder
to which the symbolic link points. However, when you delete a symbolic link,
you delete the link file, not the file to which the symbolic link points.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To create a symbolic link to a file or folder, select the file or folder
to which you want to create a link. Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Make Link</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. A link to the
file or folder is added to the current folder. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">Alternatively, grab the item to which you want to create a link, then
press-and-hold <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap></keycombo>. Drag the item
to the location where you want to place the link.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">By default, the file manager adds an emblem to symbolic links.</para>
      <note>
        <para xml:lang="en">The permissions of a symbolic link are determined by the file
or folder to which a symbolic link points.</para>
      </note>
      <tip><para xml:lang="en">For more on dragging items, see <xref linkend="caja-dragndrop"/>.</para></tip>      
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-476"><info><title>การดูคุณสมบัติของแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>viewing properties</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การดูคุณสมบัติของแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder whose properties you want to view.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. A properties dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Use the properties dialog to view the properties of the file or folder. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to close the properties dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para xml:lang="en">The following table lists the properties that you can view or set for files and folders, the exact information shown depends on the object type:</para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="27.27*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="72.73*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para xml:lang="en">Property</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>ชื่อ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The name of the file or folder. You can change the name here and the file or folder will be renamed when you click on <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>ชนิด</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The type of object, file or folder for example.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>ตำแหน่ง</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The system path for the object. This represents where the object is situated on your computer, relative to the system root.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>ปริมาตร</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The volume on which a folder resides. This is the physical location of the folder, on which media it resides, for example which hard disk or CD-ROM drive.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Free space</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The amount of free space on the media upon which a folder resides. This represents the maximum amount of data you can copy to this folder.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para>MIME Type</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The official naming of the type of file.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Modified</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The date and time at which the object was last changed.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Accessed</para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">The date and time at which the object was last viewed.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-permissions-overview" status="review"><info><title>การกำหนดสิทธิ์ของแฟ้ม</title></info>
        <para xml:lang="en">Permissions are settings assigned to each file and folder
  that determine what type of access users can have to the file or folder. For example, you can determine whether other users can read and edit a file that belongs to you, or only have access to read it but not make changes to it.</para>
        <para xml:lang="en">Each file belongs to a particular user, and is associated with a group that the owner belongs to. The super user "root" has the ability to access any file on the system.</para>
        <para xml:lang="en">You can set permissions for three categories of users:</para>        
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry><term>เจ้าของ</term>
            <listitem>
              <para xml:lang="en">The user that created the file or folder.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>กลุ่ม</term>
            <listitem>
              <para xml:lang="en">A group of users to which the owner belongs.</para>
            </listitem>     
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>อื่นๆ</term>
            <listitem>
              <para xml:lang="en">All other users not already included.</para>
            </listitem>     
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <para xml:lang="en">For each category of user, different permissions can be set. These behave differently for files and folders, as follows:
        </para>
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry><term>อ่าน</term>
            <listitem>          
            <para xml:lang="en">Files can be opened</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Directory contents can be displayed</para>
            </listitem>          
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term>เขียน</term>
            <listitem>          
            <para xml:lang="en">Files can be edited or deleted</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Directory contents can be modified</para>
             </listitem>          
         </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry><term xml:lang="en">execute</term>
            <listitem>          
            <para xml:lang="en">Executable files can be run as a program</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Directories can be entered</para>
            </listitem>          
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>        

        <para xml:lang="en">For more on changing the permissions for a file or folder, see <xref linkend="caja-permissions"/>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-permissions"><info><title>การเปลี่ยนการกำหนดสิทธิ์</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-430"/>
      
      <section xml:id="caja-permissions-file"><info><title>การเปลี่ยนการกำหนดสิทธิ์ของแฟ้ม</title></info>    
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>file manager</primary>
          <secondary>changing permissions</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>permissions</primary>
          <secondary>changing file</secondary>
        </indexterm>      
        <para xml:lang="en">To change the permissions of a file, perform the following steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Select the file that you want to change. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <xref linkend="caja-properties"/> for the item is displayed.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Click on the <guilabel>Permissions</guilabel> tab.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">To change the file's group, choose from the groups the user belongs to in the drop-down selector.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>          
            <para xml:lang="en">For each of the owner, the group, and all other users, choose from these permissions for the file:</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry><term>ไม่มี</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para xml:lang="en">No access to the file is possible. (You can't set this for the owner.)</para>
                </listitem>     
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry><term>อ่านได้เท่านั้น</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para xml:lang="en">The users can open a file to see its contents, but not make any changes.</para>
                </listitem>     
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry><term>อ่านและเขียนได้</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para xml:lang="en">Normal access to a file is possible: it can be opened and saved.</para>
                </listitem>     
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">To allow a file to be run as a program, select <guilabel>Execute</guilabel></para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>   
      </section>    

      <section xml:id="caja-permissions-folder"><info><title>การเปลี่ยนการกำหนดสิทธิ์ของโฟลเดอร์</title></info>    
        
        
        <para xml:lang="en">To change the permissions of a folder, perform the following steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Select the folder that you want to change. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <xref linkend="caja-properties"/> for the item is displayed.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Click on the <guilabel>Permissions</guilabel> tab.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">To change the folder's group, choose from the groups the user belongs to in the drop-down selector.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>          
            <para xml:lang="en">For each of the owner, the group, and all other users, choose from these folder access permissions:</para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry><term>ไม่มี</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para xml:lang="en">No access to the folder is possible. (You can't set this for the owner.)</para>
                </listitem>     
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry><term>ดูรายชื่อแฟ้มเท่านั้น</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para xml:lang="en">The users can see the items in the folder, but not open any of them.</para>
                </listitem>     
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry><term>เข้าถึงแฟ้ม</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para xml:lang="en">Items in the folder can be opened and modified, provided their own permissions allow it.</para>
                </listitem>     
              </varlistentry>
              <varlistentry><term>สร้างและลบแฟ้ม</term>
                <listitem>
                  <para xml:lang="en">The user can create new files and delete files in the folder, in addition to being able to access existing files.</para>
                </listitem>     
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>  
       
        <para xml:lang="en">To set permissions for all the items contained in a folder, set the <guilabel>File Access</guilabel> and <guilabel>Execute</guilabel> properties and click on <guibutton>Apply permissions to enclosed files</guibutton>.</para>
      </section>           

    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="goscaja-200"><info><title>การเพิ่มหมายเหตุให้กับแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can add notes to files or folders. You can add notes to files or
folders in the following ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">From the properties dialog</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">From <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> in the side pane</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <section xml:id="caja-notes"><info><title>การเพิ่มหมายเหตุโดยใช้กล่องโต้ตอบคุณสมบัติ</title></info>
        <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
        <anchor xml:id="goscaja-472"/>           
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>notes</primary>
          <secondary>adding to files and folders</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>file manager</primary>
          <secondary>notes</secondary>
          <tertiary>adding</tertiary>
        </indexterm>
        <para xml:lang="en">To add a note
to a file or folder, perform the following steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder to which you want to add a note. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <xref linkend="caja-properties"/> for the item is displayed.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Click on the <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> tab. In the <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> tabbed section, type the note.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to close the properties
dialog. A note emblem is added to the file or folder.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>notes</primary><secondary>deleting</secondary></indexterm><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>file manager</primary><secondary>notes</secondary><tertiary>deleting</tertiary></indexterm>To delete a note, delete the note text from the <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="goscaja-473"><info><title>การเพิ่มหมายเหตุโดยใช้หัวข้อหมายเหตุในแถบข้าง</title></info>
        
        <para xml:lang="en">To add a note to a file or folder, perform the following steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Open the file or folder to which you want to add a note in
the view pane.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <guilabel>Notes</guilabel> from the drop-down list
at the top of the side pane. To display the side pane, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Side Pane</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Type the note in the side pane. A note emblem is added to
the file or folder in the view pane, and a note icon is added to the side
pane. You can click on this icon to display the note.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para xml:lang="en">To delete a note, delete the note text from <guilabel>Notes</guilabel>
in the side pane.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-bookmarks"><info><title>การใช้ที่คั่นหน้าสำหรับตำแหน่งที่ตั้งที่คุณใช้บ่อย</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-36"/>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>bookmarks</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can keep a list of <firstterm>bookmarks</firstterm> in <application>Caja</application>: folders and other locations that you frequently need to open.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">Your bookmarks are listed in the following places:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
    	  <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The <guimenu>Places</guimenu> menu on the top panel.</para></listitem>
    	  <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The <guimenu>Places</guimenu> menu in a folder window.</para></listitem>
    	  <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The <guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu> menu in a <application>Caja</application> browser window.</para></listitem>
    	  <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The side pane in the <xref linkend="filechooser-open"/>. This allows you to quickly open a file that is in one of your bookmarked locations.</para></listitem>
    	  <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The list of commonly used locations in the <xref linkend="filechooser-save"/>. This allows you to quickly save a file to a location you have in your bookmarks.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para xml:lang="en">To open an item that is in your bookmarks, choose the item from a menu.</para>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-40"><info><title>การเพิ่มที่คั่นหน้า</title></info>
        <para xml:lang="en">To add a bookmark, open the folder or location that you want to bookmark, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Places</guimenu><guimenuitem>Add Bookmark</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
        <para xml:lang="en">If you are using a <application>Caja</application> browser window, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu><guimenuitem>Add Bookmark</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-41"><info><title>การแก้ไขที่คั่นหน้า</title></info>
        <para>การแก้ไขที่คั่นหน้า ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Places</guimenu><guimenuitem>Edit Bookmarks</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, or in a browser window, <menuchoice><guimenu>Bookmarks</guimenu><guimenuitem>Edit Bookmarks</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. An <guilabel>Edit Bookmarks</guilabel>
dialog is displayed. </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">Select the bookmark on the left side of
the <guilabel>Edit Bookmarks</guilabel> dialog. Edit the details for the bookmark
on the right side of the <guilabel>Edit Bookmarks</guilabel> dialog, as follows:</para>
            <informaltable frame="topbot">
              <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <colspec colwidth="27.27*"/>
                <colspec colwidth="72.73*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row rowsep="1">
                    <entry>
                      <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry valign="top">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>Name</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry valign="top">
                      <para xml:lang="en">Use this text box to specify the name that identifies the
bookmark in the menus.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry valign="top">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>Location</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry valign="top">
                      <para xml:lang="en">Use this field to specify the location of the bookmark.</para>
                      <para xml:lang="en">Folders on your system use the <uri>file:///</uri> URI.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">To delete a bookmark, select the bookmark on the left side
of the dialog. Click <guilabel>Delete</guilabel>. </para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-trash"><info><title>การใช้ถังขยะ</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-44"/>         
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_trash_launcher.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>Trash icon, empty.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>Trash</primary>
        <secondary>introduction</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">Trash is a special folder that holds files that you no longer want to keep.
Files in the Trash are not deleted permanently until you empty the trash. This two-stage process is in 
case you change your mind, or accidentally remove the wrong file.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can move the following items to <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Files</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>โฟลเดอร์</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Desktop objects</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para xml:lang="en">If you need to retrieve a file from <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>, you
can display <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> and move the file out of <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>. When you empty <guilabel>Trash</guilabel>, you delete the
contents of <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> permanently. </para>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-107"><info><title>การแสดงถังขยะ</title></info>
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>Trash</primary>
          <secondary>displaying</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para xml:lang="en">You can display the contents of <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> in the following
ways:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">From a file browser window</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Go</guimenu><guimenuitem>Trash</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The contents of <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> are displayed in
the window.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">From a spatial window</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Places</guimenu><guimenuitem>Trash</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The contents of <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> are
displayed in the window.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">From the desktop</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Double-click on the <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> object on the desktop.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="goscaja-108"><info><title>การเทถังขยะ</title></info>
        
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>Trash</primary>
          <secondary>emptying</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para xml:lang="en">You can empty the contents of <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> in the following
ways:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">From a file browser window</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Empty
Trash</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para xml:lang="en">From the desktop</para>
            <para xml:lang="en">Right-click on the <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> object, then choose <guimenuitem>Empty Trash</guimenuitem>.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
   <caution>
    <para xml:lang="en">When you empty trash, you destroy all files in the trash. Be sure that the trash only contains files
you no longer need.
    </para>
   </caution>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-hidden-files"><info><title>แฟ้มซ่อน</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>hidden</primary>
        <secondary>files</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">By default, <application>Caja</application> does not display certain system and backup files in folders. This prevents accidental modification or deletion of them, which  can impair the operation of your computer, and also reduces clutter in locations such as your Home Folder. Caja does not display:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Hidden files, whose filename begins with a period (.),</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Backup files, whose filename ends with a tilde (~)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Files that are listed in a particular folder's <filename>.hidden</filename> file.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para xml:lang="en">You may hide or show hidden files in a particular folder by selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Hidden Files</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, or by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo>.</para>
      
      <para xml:lang="en">To set <application>Caja</application> to always show hidden files, see  <xref linkend="caja-preferences"/>.</para>

      <section xml:id="caja-managing-hidden-files"><info><title>การซ่อนแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
        <indexterm xml:lang="en">
          <primary>create</primary>
          <secondary>hidden</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para xml:lang="en">To hide a file or folder in <application>Caja</application>, either rename the file so its name begins with the period (.) character, or create a text file named <filename>.hidden</filename> in the same folder, and add its name to it, as in the example below:</para>
        <programlisting xml:lang="en">filename
foldername</programlisting>
        <para xml:lang="en">You may need to refresh the relevant <application>Caja</application> window to see the change: press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo>.</para>
      </section>
  </section>
  </section>
  <!-- ====================================================== File properties -->    

  <section xml:id="caja-properties"><info><title>คุณสมบัติของรายการ</title></info>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-51"/><!-- was: changing icon, but linked to from the GUI -->

    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>properties</secondary>
    </indexterm>    
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>file properties</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para xml:lang="en">
      The <guilabel>Item Properties</guilabel> window shows more information about any file, folder, or other item in the file manager. With this window, you can also do the following:</para> 
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Change the icon for an item: see <xref linkend="caja-icon"/>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Add or remove emblems for an item: see <xref linkend="caja-emblems"/>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Change the UNIX file permissions for an item: see <xref linkend="caja-permissions"/>.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Choose which application is used to open an item, and others of the same type.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Add notes to an item: see <xref linkend="caja-notes"/>.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para xml:lang="en">To open the item properties window, perform the following steps:</para>
    <orderedlist>
	    <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Select the item whose properties you want to examine or change. If you select more than one item, the properties window will show the properties that are in common to all items.</para></listitem>
	    <listitem>
	      <para xml:lang="en">Do one of the following:</para>
  	      <itemizedlist>
        	  <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice>
  <guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Right-click on the selected item and choose <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Return</keycap></keycombo>.</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
	    </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>  
  
  <!-- ====================================================== Appearance -->  
  <section xml:id="goscaja-203"><info><title>การปรับรูปแบบการแสดงแฟ้มและโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>modifying appearance of files and folders</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para xml:lang="en">The <application>Caja</application> file manager enables you to modify the appearance of your files and folders in several ways. You may customize the way files or folders look by attaching emblems or backgrounds to them. You can also change format in which <application>Caja</application> displays these items to you. The following sections describe how to do so.</para>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-550"><info><title>ไอคอนและตรา</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>icons</secondary>
        <tertiary>introduction</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>emblems</secondary>
        <see>emblems</see>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>emblems</primary>
        <secondary>introduction</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">The file manager displays your files and folders as icons. Depending on the type of the file the icon may be a image representative of the file type, a small thumbnail or preview showing the files contents. You can also add emblems to your file and folder icons. Such emblems appear in addition to the file icon and provide another means to manage your files. For example you can mark a file as important by adding an <guilabel>Important</guilabel> emblem to it, creating the following visual effect: </para>
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_emblem.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>File icon with Important emblem.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
      
      <para xml:lang="en">Notice how the file on the left is distinguished from the file on the right by the addition of the <guilabel>Important (!)</guilabel> emblem to its icon. See <xref linkend="caja-emblems"/> for more on adding emblems.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">The file manager automatically applies emblems for the following types of files:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Symbolic links</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Items for which you have the following permissions:<indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>permissions</primary><secondary>and emblems</secondary></indexterm></para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para xml:lang="en">No read permission</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para xml:lang="en">No write permission</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para xml:lang="en">The following table shows the default emblems:</para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para xml:lang="en">Default Emblem</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_link_emblem.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>Symbolic link emblem.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>symbolic links</primary><secondary>and emblems</secondary></indexterm>Symbolic link</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_nowrite_emblem.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>No write permission emblem.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">No write permission</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <screenshot>
                  <mediaobject xml:lang="en">
                    <imageobject>
                      <imagedata fileref="figures/caja_noread_emblem.png" format="PNG"/>
                    </imageobject>
                    <textobject>
                      <phrase>No read permission emblem.</phrase>
                    </textobject>
                  </mediaobject>
                </screenshot>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">No read permission</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="caja-icon"><info><title>การเปลี่ยนไอคอนของแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
       
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>icons</secondary>
        <tertiary>changing</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">To change the icon that represents an
individual file or folder, perform the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the file or folder that you want to change.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <xref linkend="caja-properties"/> for the item is displayed. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">On the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> tabbed section, click on
the current <guibutton>Icon</guibutton>. A <guilabel>Select custom 
icon</guilabel> dialog is displayed. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Use the <guilabel>Select custom icon</guilabel> dialog to choose
the icon to represent the file or folder. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to close the properties dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para xml:lang="en">To restore an icon from a custom icon to the default icon,
Select the file or folder that you want to change, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
click on the <guibutton>Icon</guibutton> button, in the <guilabel>Select custom 
icon</guilabel> dialog click <guibutton>Revert</guibutton>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-emblems"><info><title>การเพิ่มตราให้กับแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-112"/>       
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>emblems</primary>
        <secondary>adding to file</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>emblems</primary>
        <secondary>adding to folder</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การเพิ่มตราให้กับแฟ้มหรือโฟลเดอร์ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the item to which you want to add an emblem.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Right-click on the item, then choose <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>. The <xref linkend="caja-properties"/> for the item is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click on the <guilabel>Emblems</guilabel> tab to display the <guilabel>Emblems</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Select the emblem to add to the item.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to close the properties dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para xml:lang="en">In browser windows you may also add emblems to items by dragging them from the emblem side pane.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-471"><info><title>การสร้างตราใหม่</title></info>
      
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>emblems</primary>
        <secondary>adding new</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>การสร้างตราใหม่ ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Backgrounds and Emblems</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click on the <guibutton>Emblem</guibutton> button, then click
on the <guibutton>Add a New Emblem</guibutton> button. A <guilabel>Create
a New Emblem</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Type a name for the emblem in the <guilabel>Keyword</guilabel> text box.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click on the <guilabel>Image</guilabel> button. A dialog is
displayed, click <guibutton>Browse</guibutton>. When you choose an emblem,
click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> on the <guilabel>Create a
New Emblem</guilabel> dialog.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-backgrounds-and-emblems"><info><title>การเปลี่ยนพื้นหลัง</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-50"/>         
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-63"/>
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-64"/>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>changing backgrounds</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>backgrounds</primary>
        <secondary>changing screen component</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">The file manager includes background patterns and emblems that you can
      use to change the appearance of your folders.  Background patterns and emblems
      can also be used on the desktop, on folders and certain side panes in the file
      browser, and on panels.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To change the background of a window, pane, or panel,  perform the following
      steps: </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Backgrounds and Emblems</guimenuitem></menuchoice>
          in any file manager window. The <guilabel>Backgrounds and Emblems</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Click the <guibutton>Patterns</guibutton> button or the <guibutton>Colors</guibutton>
          button to see a list of background patterns or background colors you can use.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">To change the background, drag a pattern or color to the desired window, pane, or panel.
          To reset the background, drag the <guilabel>Reset</guilabel> entry to the desired window, pane,
          or panel.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>

      <para xml:lang="en">You can set the background of all folders in the file manager by dragging a pattern
      or color with your right or middle mouse button.  When you release the drag, you will see
      a popup menu with the option to set the pattern or color as the background for all folders.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">You can add a new pattern to the list by clicking the <guibutton>Add a New Pattern</guibutton>
      button when the patterns are selected.  Locate an image file in the file chooser dialog and click
      <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.  The image file will appear in the list of patterns you can use.</para>

      <para xml:lang="en">You can add a new color to the list by clicking the <guibutton>Add a New Color</guibutton>
      button when the colors are selected.  Select a color in the color chooser dialog and click
      <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.  The color will appear in the list of colors you can use.</para>
    </section>    
  </section>  
  
  <!-- ====================================================== Removable media -->    
  <section xml:id="goscaja-460"><info><title>การใช้สื่อถอดเสียบ</title></info>
    <!-- compatibility -->
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-469"/>

    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>removable media</primary>
      <secondary>introduction</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para xml:lang="en">
      The file manager can initiate various actions when removable media appear,
      such as mounting it, opening a file manager window showing its contents,
      or running a suitable application that can handle it (for example a music
      player for an audio CD). See <xref linkend="goscaja-61"/> for how to
      configure these actions for different media formats.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-462"><info><title>การเมานท์สื่อ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>removable media</primary>
        <secondary>mounting</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">To <firstterm>mount</firstterm> media is to make the file
system of the media available for access. When you mount media, the file system
of the media is attached as a subdirectory to your file system.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To mount media, insert the media in the appropriate device. An icon 
that represents the media is added to the desktop. The icon is added only
if your system is configured to mount the device automatically when media
is detected. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">If your system is not configured to mount the device automatically,
you must mount the device manually. Double-click on the <guilabel>Computer</guilabel> icon from the desktop. A <guilabel>Computer </guilabel> dialog
is displayed. Double-click on the icon that represents the media. For example,
to mount a floppy diskette, double-click on the <guilabel>Floppy</guilabel>
icon. An icon that represents the media is added to the desktop. </para>
      <note>
        <para xml:lang="en">You cannot change the name of a removable media icon.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-461"><info><title>การแสดงเนื้อหาของสื่อ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>removable media</primary>
        <secondary>displaying media contents</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can display media contents in any of the following ways: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Double-click on the icon that represents the media on the desktop.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Right-click on the icon that represents the media on the
desktop, then choose <guimenuitem>Open</guimenuitem>. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para xml:lang="en">A file manager window displays the contents of the media. To reload
the display, click on the <guibutton>Reload</guibutton> button.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-463"><info><title>การแสดงคุณสมบัติของสื่อ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>removable media</primary>
        <secondary>displaying media properties</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">To display the properties of removable media,
right-click on the icon that represents the media on the desktop, then choose <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem>. A dialog displays the properties of the media.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To close the properties dialog, click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-464"><info><title>การดันสื่อออก</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>removable media</primary>
        <secondary>ejecting</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">To eject media, right-click on the media icon on the desktop,
then choose <guimenuitem>Eject</guimenuitem>. If the drive for the media is
a motorized drive, the media is ejected from the drive. If the drive for the
media is not motorized, wait until the desktop icon for the media disappears,
then eject the media manually.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">You cannot eject media from a motorized drive when the media is mounted.
To eject media, first unmount the media. For example, to remove a USB flash drive, perform the following steps:</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Close all file manager windows, <application>Terminal</application>
windows, and any other windows that access the USB drive. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Right-click on the icon that represents the drive on
the desktop, then choose <guimenuitem>Eject</guimenuitem>. The desktop icon
for the drive disappears.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">Remove the USB flash drive.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
          <caution>
            <para xml:lang="en">You must unmount removable media before ejecting. Do not remove a USB flash drive before you unmount the flash drive. If you do not unmount the media first you might lose data.</para>
          </caution>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="caja-cdwriter"><info><title>การเขียนซีดีหรือดีวีดี</title></info>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-475"/>

    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>writing CDs</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>CDs, writing</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>writing CDs</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>burning CDs</primary>
      <see>writing CDs</see>
    </indexterm>
    <para xml:lang="en">Writing to a CD or DVD may be useful for backing up your important documents. To do this, your computer must have a CD or DVD writer.    
    </para>
    <tip><para xml:lang="en">A simple way to check what sort of CD or DVD drive your computer has is to choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Places</guimenu><guimenuitem>Computer</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the top panel menubar. If the icon for your CD drive has terms like "CD-RW" or "DVD(+-)R" in its label, then your computer is able to write discs.</para></tip>
    
    <para xml:lang="en">You can start choosing files to burn to a disc at any time. The file manager provides
a special folder for files and folders that you wish to write to a CD or DVD. From there you can easily write all the content (which you place in this special folder) to a CD or DVD.</para>

    <section xml:id="caja-cdwriter-data"><info><title>การสร้างแผ่นข้อมูล</title></info>
      
    <para>การเขียนแผ่นซีดีหรือดีวีดี ทำได้ตามขั้นตอนต่อไปนี้:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">Open <menuchoice><guimenu>Applications</guimenu><guimenu>System Tools</guimenu><guimenuitem>CD/DVD Creator</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The file manager opens the CD/DVD Creator folder.</para>
        <note><para xml:lang="en">In a File Browser window, the <guimenuitem>CD/DVD Creator</guimenuitem> item is available in the <guimenu>Go</guimenu> menu.</para></note>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">Drag the files and folders that you want to write to CD or DVD to
the CD/DVD Creator folder.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">Insert a writable CD or DVD into the CD/DVD writer device on your system.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">Press the <guibutton>Write to Disc</guibutton> button, or choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Write to CD/DVD</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. A <guilabel>Write to Disc</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">Use the <guilabel>Write to Disc</guilabel>
dialog to specify how you want to write the CD, as follows:</para>
        <informaltable frame="topbot">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
            <thead>
              <row rowsep="1">
                <entry>
                  <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Write disc to</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">Select the device to which you want to write the
CD from the drop-down list. To create an CD image file, select the <guilabel>File image</guilabel> option. A CD image file is a normal file that contains all the data in the same format as a CD, that you can write to a CD later.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Disc name</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">Type a name for the CD in the text box.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Data size</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">Shows the size of the data to be written to disc.
The blank disk must be at least this size.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>Write speed</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">Select the speed at which you want to write the
CD from the drop-down list.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">Click on the <guibutton>Write</guibutton> button. </para>
        <para xml:lang="en">If you selected the <guilabel>File image</guilabel> option from the <guilabel>Target to write to</guilabel> drop-down list, a <guilabel>Choose a filename
for the disc image</guilabel> dialog is displayed. Use the dialog to specify
the location where you want to save the disc image file. By default, disc image
files have a <filename>.iso</filename> file extension.</para>
        <para xml:lang="en">A <guilabel>Writing disc</guilabel> dialog is displayed. This process takes some time. When the disc is
written or when the disc image file is created, a message to indicate that the
process is complete is displayed in the dialog.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <tip><para xml:lang="en">You can set the CD/DVD Creator folder to open automatically when you insert a blank disc. See <xref linkend="goscaja-61"/>.</para></tip>
    <note><para xml:lang="en">The filesystem written to the CD will be readable with long filenames on all recent operating systems. Both the Joliet and the Rock Ridge CD-ROM filesystem extensions are used.</para></note>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-cdwriter-copy"><info><title>การทำสำเนาซีดีหรือดีวีดี</title></info>
        <para xml:lang="en">You can create a copy of a CD or DVD, either to another disc or to an image file stored on your computer. To create a copy, perform the following steps:</para>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Insert the disc you want to copy.</para></listitem>               
          <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Places</guimenu><guimenuitem>Computer</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from the top panel menubar.</para></listitem>       
          <listitem><para xml:lang="en">Right-click on the CD icon, and choose <guimenuitem>Copy Disc</guimenuitem>.</para></listitem>       
          <listitem><para xml:lang="en">The <guilabel>Write to Disc</guilabel> dialog is displayed.</para></listitem>  
        </orderedlist>
        <para xml:lang="en">If you have only one drive with write capabilities, the process will first create a disc image file on your computer. It will then eject the original disk, and ask you to change it for a blank disk on which to write the copy.</para>
        <tip><para xml:lang="en">If you want to create more than one copy, choose the Image File option on the <guilabel>Write to Disc</guilabel> and then write the disc image: see <xref linkend="caja-cdwriter-writeimage"/>.</para></tip>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-cdwriter-writeimage"><info><title>การเขียนแผ่นจากแฟ้มอิมเมจ</title></info>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can write a disc image to a CD or DVD. For example, you may have downloaded a disc image from the internet, or previously created one yourself. Disc images usually have a <filename>.iso</filename> file extension and are sometimes called iso files.</para>
        <para xml:lang="en">To write a disc image, right-click on the disc image file, then choose <guimenuitem>Write to Disc</guimenuitem> from the popup menu.</para>      
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="goscaja-515"><info><title>การท่องดูเซิร์ฟเวอร์ในเครือข่าย</title></info>
    <para xml:lang="en">The <application>Caja</application> file manager provides an integrated
access point to your files, applications, FTP sites, Windows shares, WebDav servers and SSH servers.</para>

    <section xml:id="caja-server-connect"><info><title>การเข้าถึงเซิร์ฟเวอร์ในเครือข่าย</title></info>
      <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-37"/>      
      <!-- MOVE THIS ANCHOR -->
      <!-- To Add a Network Server -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-466"/>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>FTP sites</primary>
        <secondary>accessing</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>FTP sites</secondary>
        <see>FTP sites</see>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can use the file manager to access
a remote server, be it an FTP site, a Windows share, a WebDav server or an SSH server.</para>
<para xml:lang="en">To access a remote server, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Connect to Server</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
You may also access this dialog from the menubar by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>Places</guimenu><guimenuitem>Connect to Server</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
<para xml:lang="en">To connect to a remote server, start by choosing the service type, then enter the server address.</para>
<para xml:lang="en">If required by your server, you may provide the following optional information : </para>
            <informaltable frame="topbot">
              <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
                <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="27.27*"/>
                <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="72.73*"/>
                <thead>
                  <row rowsep="1">
                    <entry>
                      <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry>
                      <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                </thead>
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry valign="top">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>Port</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry valign="top">
                      <para xml:lang="en">Port to connect to on the server. This should only be used if it is necessary to
change the default port, you would normally leave this blank.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry valign="top">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>Folder</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry valign="top">
                        <para xml:lang="en">Folder to open upon connecting to server.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry colname="colspec0">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>User Name</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry colname="colspec1">
                      <para xml:lang="en">The user name of the account used to connect to the server.
This should be supplied with the connection information if needed.
The user name information is not appropriate for a public FTP connection.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry colname="colspec0">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>Name to use for connection</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry colname="colspec1">
                      <para xml:lang="en">The designation of the connection as it will appear in the file manager.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry colname="colspec0">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>Share</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry colname="colspec1">
                      <para xml:lang="en">Name of desired windows share. This is only applicable to Windows shares.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry colname="colspec0">
                      <para xml:lang="en">
                        <guilabel>Domain name</guilabel>
                      </para>
                    </entry>
                    <entry colname="colspec1">
                      <para xml:lang="en">Windows domain. This is only applicable to Windows shares.</para>
                    </entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </informaltable>
<para xml:lang="en">If the server information is provided in the form of a URI, or you require a specialized connection, choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Custom Location</guimenuitem></menuchoice> as the service type.</para>
<para xml:lang="en">Once you have filled in the information, click on
the <guibutton>Connect</guibutton> button. When the connection succeeds, the contents of the site are displayed and you may drag and drop files to and from the remote server.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="caja-accessnetwork"><info><title>การเข้าถึงที่หลัก ๆ ในเครือข่าย</title></info>
      <!-- MOVE THIS ANCHOR -->
      <!-- To Add a Network Server -->
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-508"/>
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-509"/>
      <anchor xml:id="goscaja-465"/>

      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>network places</primary>
        <secondary>accessing</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>network places</secondary>
        <see>network places</see>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">If your system is configured
to access places on a network, you can use the file manager to access the
network places. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To access network places, open the file manager and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Places</guimenu><guimenuitem>Network Servers</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. A window opens that displays the network places that you
can access. Double-click on the network that you want to access. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>NFS servers</primary><see>Unix network</see></indexterm>To
access UNIX shares, double-click on the <guilabel>Unix Network (NFS) </guilabel>
object. A list of the UNIX shares available to you is displayed in the file
manager window.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>Samba servers</primary><see>Windows network</see></indexterm>To access Windows shares, double-click on the <guilabel>Windows
Network (SMB) </guilabel> object. A list of the Windows shares available to
you is displayed in the file manager window.</para>
    </section>

    <!-- special URIs by and large obsolete or at least arcane -->
    <section xml:id="goscaja-467"><info><title>การเข้าถึงตำแหน่ง URI พิเศษ</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>special URI locations</primary>
        <secondary>accessing</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>special URI locations</secondary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>URI, special</primary>
        <see>special URI locations</see>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">Caja has certain special URI locations that enable you to access particular functions from the file manager.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">These are intended for advanced users: in most cases, an easier method of accessing the function or location exists.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en"><xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-479"/> lists the special URI locations that you can
use with the file manager.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-479"><info><title xml:lang="en">Special URI Locations</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33.94*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="66.06*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para xml:lang="en">URI Location</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <command>burn:///</command>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">This is a special location where you can copy files and folders that you want to write
to a CD. From here you can write the contents of the location to a CD easily. See also <xref linkend="caja-cdwriter"/>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <command>network:///</command>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Displays network locations to
which you can connect, if your system is configured to access locations on
a network. To access a network location, double-click on the network location.
You can also use this URI to add network locations to your system. See also <xref linkend="caja-accessnetwork"/>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>
  </section>

  <!-- ============================================== prefs -->
  <section xml:id="caja-preferences"><info><title>การปรับแต่ง Caja</title></info>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.12 -->
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-15"/>
    <anchor xml:id="goscaja-17"/>
    <!-- preserve id for backwards compatibility: 2.16 -->    
    <anchor xml:id="prefs-filemanager"/>
    <anchor xml:id="goscustdesk-84"/>

    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>customizing</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>preferences</secondary>
      <tertiary>introduction</tertiary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>preferences, file manager</primary>
      <see>file manager preferences</see>
    </indexterm>
    <para xml:lang="en">Use the <guilabel>File Management Preferences</guilabel> dialog to customize the file manager to suit your requirements
and preferences.</para>
    <para xml:lang="en">To display the <guilabel>File Management Preferences</guilabel> dialog, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You can also access this dialog directly from the top panel Menubar
by choosing <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>File Management</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
    <para xml:lang="en">You can set preferences in the following categories: </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">The default settings for views.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">The behavior of files and folders, executable text files, and Trash.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">The information that is displayed in icon captions and the date format.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">The columns that appear in the list view and their order.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">Preview options to improve the performance of the file manager.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para xml:lang="en">How removable media and connected devices are handled.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-438"><info><title>การปรับแต่งมุมมอง</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>preferences</secondary>
        <tertiary>views</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can specify a default view,
and select sort options and display options. You can also specify default
settings for icon views and list views.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To specify your default view settings,
choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Click on the <guilabel>Views</guilabel> tab to
display the <guilabel>Views</guilabel> tabbed section.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en"><xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-30"/> lists the views preferences that
you can modify. </para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-30"><info><title>การปรับแต่งมุมมอง</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>View new folders using</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select the default view for folders. When you open
a folder, the folder is displayed in the view that you select. This can be the icon view, the list view, or the compact view, which is a variant of the icon view that is organized in columns rather than rows..</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Arrange items</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select the characteristic by which you want to sort
the items in folders that are displayed in this view.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Sort folders before files</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to list folders before
files when you sort a folder.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Show hidden and backup files</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to display files that are normally not shown in folders. For more on hidden files, see <xref linkend="caja-hidden-files"/>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Default zoom level</guilabel> in the Icon View, Compact View, or List View sections
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select the default zoom level for folders that are displayed
in this view. The zoom level specifies the size of items in a view.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Use compact layout</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select
this option to arrange the items in icon view so that the items in the folder
are closer to each other.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Text beside icons</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to place the icon captions
for items beside the icon rather than under the icon.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>All columns have the same width</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to make all columns in a compact view have the same width.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Show only folders</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to display only folders in the <guilabel>Tree</guilabel> in the side pane.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-56"><info><title>การปรับแต่งพฤติกรรม</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>preferences</secondary>
        <tertiary>behavior</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">To set your preferences for
files and folders, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Click on the <guilabel>Behavior</guilabel>
tab to display the <guilabel>Behavior</guilabel> tabbed section. You can set the following preferences:</para>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Single click to open items</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to perform the default action
      for an item when you click on the item. When this option is selected, and
      you point to an item, the title of the item is underlined. </para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Double click to open items</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to perform the default action for an item when you double-click
      on the item.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Always open in browser windows</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to use <application>Caja</application> in browser mode
      rather than spatial mode. Selecting this lets you browse your files and folders in the same window, otherwise you will navigate your files and folders as objects.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Run executable text files when they are opened</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to run an text executable file when you choose
      the file. An executable text file is a text file that can execute, that
      is, a shell script.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>View executable text files when they are opened</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to display the contents of an executable text file when you
      choose the executable text file.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Ask each time</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select
      this option to display a dialog when you choose an executable text file. The dialog
      asks whether you want to execute the file or display the file. </para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Ask before emptying the Trash or deleting files</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to display a confirmation message before <guilabel>Trash</guilabel> is emptied, or files are deleted. Leave this selected unless you have good reason not to.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
       	<varlistentry>
      	  <term xml:lang="en"><guilabel>Include a Delete command that bypasses Trash</guilabel></term>
      	  <listitem>
      	    <para xml:lang="en">Select this option to add a <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> menu item to
      the following menus:</para>
                      <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem>
                          <para xml:lang="en">The <guimenu>Edit</guimenu> menu.</para>
                        </listitem>
                        <listitem>
                          <para xml:lang="en">The popup menu that is displayed when you right-click on a
      file, folder, or desktop  object. </para>
                        </listitem>
                      </itemizedlist>
                      <para xml:lang="en">When you select an item then choose the <guimenuitem>Delete</guimenuitem> menu item, the item is deleted from your file system
      immediately. There is no way to recover a deleted file. Do not select this unless you have good reason to.</para>
      	  </listitem>
      	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-439"><info><title>การปรับแต่งการแสดงผล</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>icons</secondary>
        <tertiary>caption preferences</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>preferences</secondary>
        <tertiary>icon captions</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">An icon caption displays the name of a file or folder in
an icon view. The icon caption also includes three additional items of information
on the file or folder. The additional information is displayed after the file
name. Normally only one item of information is visible, but when you zoom
in on an icon, more of the information is displayed. You can modify what additional
information is displayed in icon captions. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To set your preferences for icon captions, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
Click on the <guilabel>Display</guilabel> tab to display the <guilabel>Display</guilabel> tabbed section. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">Select the items of information that you want to display in the icon
caption from the three drop-down lists. Select the first item from the first
drop-down list, select the second item from the second drop-down list, and
so on. The following table describes the items of information that you can
select:</para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>รายละเอียด</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Size</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the size of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Type</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the description of the MIME type of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Date Modified</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the last modification date of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Date Accessed</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the date that the item was last accessed.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Owner</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the owner of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Group</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the group to which the item belongs.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Permissions</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>permissions</primary><secondary>displaying as characters</secondary></indexterm>Choose
this option to display the permissions of the item as three sets of three
characters, for example <computeroutput>-rwxrw-r--</computeroutput>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Octal Permissions</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>permissions</primary><secondary>displaying in octal notation</secondary></indexterm>Choose this option to display the permissions of the item in octal
notation, for example <computeroutput>764</computeroutput>. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>MIME Type</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the MIME type of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>None</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display no information for the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para xml:lang="en">
      The date <guilabel>Format</guilabel> option lets you choose how the date is displayed throughout Caja.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-490"><info><title>การปรับแต่งคอลัมน์ในรายชื่อ</title></info>
      <para xml:lang="en">You can specify what information is displayed in list view in file manager
windows. You can specify which columns are displayed in list view, and the
order in which the columns are displayed.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To set your preferences for list columns, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
Click on the <guilabel>List Columns</guilabel> tab to display the <guilabel>List Columns</guilabel> tabbed section. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To specify a column to display in list view, select the option that
corresponds to the column, then click on the <guibutton>Show</guibutton> button.
To remove a column from the list view, select the option that corresponds
to the column, then click on the <guibutton>Hide</guibutton> button.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">Use the <guibutton>Move Up</guibutton> and <guibutton>Move Down</guibutton>
buttons to specify the position of columns in list view.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To use the default columns and column positions, click on the <guibutton>Use Default</guibutton> button. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en">The following table describes the columns that you can display:</para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>รายละเอียด</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Name</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the name of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Size</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the size of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Type</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display
the description of the MIME type of the item from the <application>File Types
and Programs</application> preference tool.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Date Modified</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the last modification date of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Date Accessed</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the date that the item was last accessed.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Group</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the group to which the item belongs.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>MIME type</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the MIME type of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Octal Permissions</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>permissions</primary><secondary>displaying in octal notation</secondary></indexterm>Choose this
option to display the permissions of the item in octal notation, for example <computeroutput>764</computeroutput>. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Owner</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Choose this option to display the owner of the item.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Permissions</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en"><indexterm xml:lang="en"><primary>permissions</primary><secondary>displaying as characters</secondary></indexterm>Choose
this option to display the permissions of the item as three sets of three
characters, for example <computeroutput>-rwxrw-r--</computeroutput>.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-60"><info><title>การปรับแต่งการแสดงตัวอย่าง</title></info>
      <indexterm xml:lang="en">
        <primary>file manager</primary>
        <secondary>preferences</secondary>
        <tertiary>preview</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para xml:lang="en">The file manager include some
file preview features. The preview features can affect the speed with which
the file manager responds to your requests. You can modify the behavior of
some of these features to improve the speed of the file manager. For each
preview preference, you can select one of the options described in the following
table:</para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para xml:lang="en">Option</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Always</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Performs the action for both local files, and files
on other file systems.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Local Files Only</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Performs the action for local files only.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Never</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Never performs the action. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para xml:lang="en">To set your preview preferences, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Click on the <guilabel>Preview</guilabel> tab dialog to display the <guilabel>Preview</guilabel>
tabbed section. </para>
      <para xml:lang="en"><xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-41"/> lists the preview preferences that
you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-41"><info><title>การปรับแต่งการแสดงตัวอย่าง</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Show text in icons</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select an option to specify when to preview the
content of text files in the icon that represents the file. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Show thumbnails</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select
an option to specify when to show thumbnails of image files. The file manager
stores the thumbnail files for each folder in a <filename>.thumbnails</filename>
directory in the user's Home Folder.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Only for files smaller than</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Specify the maximum
file size for files for which the file manager creates a thumbnail.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Preview sound files</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select an option to specify when to preview sound files. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry colname="colspec0">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Count number of items</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry colname="colspec1">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select an option to specify when to show the
number of items in folders. When in icon view, you might
need to increase your zoom level to see the number of items in each folder.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-61"><info><title xml:lang="en">Media Preferences</title></info>
      <para xml:lang="en">
        You can configure how <application>Caja</application> handles
        removable media and devices that are connected to the computer, such
        as music players or cameras. For each media format or device 
        type, <application>Caja</application> offers to run one of the 
        applications that are known to support this format, as well as
        the following options:
      </para>
      <informaltable frame="topbot">
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para xml:lang="en">Option</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Ask what to do</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Make <application>Caja</application> ask for the desired
                   action when the media or device appears.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Do Nothing</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Do nothing.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Open Folder</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Treat the media or device like an ordinary folder and open
                it in a <application>Caja</application> window.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Open with other Application</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">Select an application to run with the <application>Caja</application> application chooser dialog. Note that applications known to handle
                the media or device can be chosen directly from the drop-down list.
                
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      <para xml:lang="en">The most common media formats can be configured in the <guilabel>Media Handling</guilabel> section: audio CDs, video DVDs, music players, cameras, and software cds.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To configure the handling for other media formats, first select the format in the <guilabel>Type</guilabel> drop-down list, then select the desired handling for this format in the <guilabel>Action</guilabel> drop-down list.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en"><xref linkend="goscaja-TBL-43"/> lists other media handling preferences that you can modify.</para>
      <table frame="topbot" xml:id="goscaja-TBL-43"><info><title>การปรับแต่งการแสดงตัวอย่าง</title></info>
        <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
          <colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="35.09*"/>
          <colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="64.91*"/>
          <thead>
            <row rowsep="1">
              <entry>
                <para>องค์ประกอบ</para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Never prompt or start programs on media insertion</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                   Select this option to prevent <application>Caja</application> from showing dialogs or running programs when media or devices appear. When this option is selected, the preferences for the handling of specific media formats are ignored.
                </para>
              </entry>
           </row>
            <row>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  <guilabel>Browse media when inserted</guilabel>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry valign="top">
                <para xml:lang="en">
                  When this option is selected, <application>Caja</application>
                  will automatically open a folder when media is inserted. This
                  only applies for media formats for which the handling has not been explicitly configured.
                </para>
              </entry>
           </row>
         </tbody>
       </tgroup>
      </table>
    </section>

  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="goscaja-440"><info><title>การขยายความสามารถ Caja</title></info>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>file manager</primary>
      <secondary>running scripts</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <indexterm xml:lang="en">
      <primary>scripts, running from file manager</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <para xml:lang="en">Caja can be extended in two main ways. Through <application>Caja</application> extensions, and through scripts. This section explains the difference between the two and how to install.</para>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-444"><info><title>สคริปต์ Caja</title></info>
      <para xml:lang="en">Caja can run scripts. Scripts are typically simpler in operation than full <application>Caja</application> extensions and can be written in any scripted language capable of being executed on your computer. To run a script choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Scripts</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, then choose the script that you want to run from the submenu.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To run a script on a particular file, select the file in the view pane.
Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guimenuitem>Scripts</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, then choose the script that you want to run on the file from
the submenu. You can also select multiple files to run your scripts on.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">You may also access scripts from the <!-- TODO link --> context menu.</para>
      <note>
        <para xml:lang="en">If you do not have any scripts installed, the script menu will not appear.</para>
      </note>

      <section xml:id="goscaja-install-scripts"><info><title>การติดตั้งสคริปต์สำหรับโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</title></info>
        <para xml:lang="en">The file manager includes a special folder where you can
store your scripts. All executable files in this folder will appear in the Scripts menu. The script folder 
is located at $HOME/.config/caja/scripts.</para>
        <para xml:lang="en">To install a script, simply copy the script to the script folder and give it the user executable permission.</para>
      <para xml:lang="en">To view the contents of your scripts folder, if you already have scripts installed, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>File</guimenu><guisubmenu>Scripts</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Open Scripts Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
You will have to navigate to the scripts folder with the file manager if you do not yet have any scripts. You may need to show hidden files for this, use <menuchoice><guimenu>View</guimenu><guimenuitem>Show Hidden Files</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para>
<para xml:lang="en">A good source to download <application>Caja</application> scripts is from the <link xlink:href="http://g-scripts.sourceforge.net"><citetitle>G-Scripts website</citetitle></link>.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="goscaja-write-scripts"><info><title>การเขียนสคริปต์สำหรับโปรแกรมจัดการแฟ้ม</title></info>
       <para xml:lang="en">When executed from a local folder, scripts will be passed the selected file names. When 
executed from a remote folder (e.g. a folder showing web or ftp content), scripts will be passed no parameters.</para>
       <para xml:lang="en">The following table shows variables passed to the script :</para>
       <informaltable frame="topbot">
          <tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
            <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
            <colspec colwidth="50*"/>
            <thead>
              <row rowsep="1">
                <entry>
                  <para xml:lang="en">Environment variable</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>คำอธิบาย</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>CAJA_SCRIPT_SELECTED_FILE_PATHS</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">newline-delimited paths for selected files (only if local)</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>CAJA_SCRIPT_SELECTED_URIS</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">newline-delimited URIs for selected files</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>CAJA_SCRIPT_CURRENT_URI</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">URI for current location</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">
                    <guilabel>CAJA_SCRIPT_WINDOW_GEOMETRY</guilabel>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry valign="top">
                  <para xml:lang="en">position and size of current window</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="caja-extensions"><info><title>ส่วนขยาย Caja</title></info>
    <para xml:lang="en"><application>Caja</application> extensions are far more powerful than <application>Caja</application> scripts, allowing more freedom where and how they extend <application>Caja</application>. <application>Caja</application> extensions are typically installed by your system administrator.</para>
    <para xml:lang="en">Some popular <application>Caja</application> extensions include:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">caja-actions</para>
          <para xml:lang="en">This extension allows you to easily assign actions based on file type</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">caja-send-to</para>
          <para xml:lang="en">This extension provides a simple way to send a file or folder to another using email, instant messaging, or Bluetooth.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para xml:lang="en">caja-open-terminal.</para>
          <para xml:lang="en">This extension provides an easy way to open a terminal at the selected starting location.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <note>
        <para xml:lang="en">If you are looking for the <guilabel>Open Terminal</guilabel> command which used to exist in the <application>Caja</application> right click menu by default then you should install the <application>caja-open-terminal</application> extension.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
